<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Exercitation answered, in the assertions following made good against it. 1 That the usurpation pretended by the exercitator is really no usurpation, by any thing that he hath said to prove it such. 2 That former oaths in controversie oblige not against obedience to present powers. 3 That obedience is due to powers in possession, though unlawfully enter'd.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1650</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 136 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 30 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A84287</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E3865</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E597_12</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R201963</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99862436</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99862436</idno>
            <idno type="VID">114595</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A84287)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 114595)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 92:E597[12])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Exercitation answered, in the assertions following made good against it. 1 That the usurpation pretended by the exercitator is really no usurpation, by any thing that he hath said to prove it such. 2 That former oaths in controversie oblige not against obedience to present powers. 3 That obedience is due to powers in possession, though unlawfully enter'd.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 45, 44-55, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for John Wright at the Kings Head in the old Bailey,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1650.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A reply to: Gee, Edward.  An exercitation concerning usurped powers.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "March 27"; "Aprill 3d 1649"; the 50 in imprint date is crossed out.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Gee, Edward, 1613-1660. --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Allegiance --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Oaths --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Obedience --  Religious aspects --  Christianity --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Commonwealth and Protectorate, 1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:114595:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>THE EXERCITATION ANSWERED, In the Aſſertions Following made good againſt it.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>1</hi> That the uſurpation pretended by the <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercitator</hi> is really no uſurpation, by any thing that he hath ſaid to prove it ſuch.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>2</hi> That former Oaths in controverſie oblige not againſt obedience to preſent Powers.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>3</hi> That obedience is due to Powers in poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, though unlawfully enter'd.</item>
            </list>
            <q>
               <p>Duobus modis aliquis eſt Tyrannus; uno, quia licet ſit verè Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minus Reipublicae, injuſtè eam adminiſtrat. Neſas eſt privatis iſium interficere; at pro ſui defenſione licet; &amp; Reſpublica quoad capita convenire poteſt, &amp; deponere &amp; depoſitum punire.</p>
               <p>Tyrannum ſecundo modo, quivis de Republica poteſt licitè inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficere niſi ex ea interfectione major a mala Reipublicae immine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent; nam tune contra Reipublicae charitatem peccaret illum in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terficiendo.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Molina de Juſtitia, Tract. 3. Diſp. 6.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, <hi>Printed for</hi> John Wright <hi>at the Kings Head in the old Bailey. 1650.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:114595:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:114595:2"/>
            <head>THE EXERCITATION anſwered, in the ASSERTIONS following, made good againſt it.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> A taſte of the Exercitator and Exercitation.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Ublique obedience to Powers ordained by God, next to immediate obedience to God himſelf ordaining thoſe Powers, is a <hi>Duty</hi> that ſhould have the firſt place in the heart, as it hath in the ſecond Table of the <hi>Law,</hi> which the <hi>New Covenant</hi> writes in the heart. And therefore he that ſhall break this Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment of obedience (not one of the leaſt but greateſt Commandments) and ſhall teach men ſo, had need of a light within him to warrant both himſelf and his Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, as cleer as the <hi>Meridian</hi> Sun; leaſt while he thinks to reſiſt the <hi>uſurpations</hi> of men, he indeed reſiſt the <hi>Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance</hi> of God.</p>
               <p>They that favour the Doctrine of diſobedience to the preſent Powers, commend to us as the moſt cleer and able if not irrefragable Diſcourſe upon that Subject, a Book intituled, <hi>An Exercitation &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Author we muſt profeſſe we know not, nor any
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:114595:3"/>thing of his perſonall ability or integrity, but certainly if in other matters he have had the repute of one defe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive in neither, we are ſory we are inforc't to ſay that in this of the <hi>Exercitation,</hi> He hath ſhewed a miſerable want of both. To make this apparent, we ſhall not need to tire the Reader or our ſelves, to follow him in his wilde extravagancies, by a particular enumeration of his tedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous impertinencies and manifeſt contradictions: It will ſuffice (before we come by an examination of his <hi>foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation</hi> and groundworke, to ſhake the main <hi>Pillars</hi> of his <hi>Philiſtine-Fabrick</hi>) that we premiſe a taſte, and but a taſte (for <hi>ex pede Herculem</hi>) of the ſtrength and candor of this ſo much admired Piece.</p>
               <p>The Title page runs, <hi>An Exercitation,</hi> ſo we may juſtly expect an accurate Tract; yet page 75. the <hi>Exercitator</hi> tels us, <hi>he hath not by him divers of the Books cited by the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour whom he there undertakes to anſwer.</hi> Hath he not? it may be they are hard to be got; or it may be they are not worth the getting, who are they? let the Reader judge, <hi>Bucer, Peter Martyr, Calvin, Gualter &amp;c.</hi> theſe are the Authors that our learned <hi>Exercitator</hi> ſaies he hath not by him; and have we not here a proper <hi>Exercitator,</hi> that thus like a freſh-water Souldier enters the Liſts without his Arms? But what want of Arms, where there is no want of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence? for he proceeds magiſterially to tell the Reader (and he muſt believe him <hi>gratis,</hi> without the leaſt ſyllable of reaſon for it) that the Authors ſayings ſet downe by his Antagoniſt reach not the caſe at all. And comes he not learnedly off? The Reader need not ſcruple to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve him that he anſwers <hi>without booke.</hi> Such an anſwer were fitter for <hi>Solomon</hi>'s ſluggard, <hi>Prov.</hi> 26.16. then an <hi>Exercitator.</hi> For ſurely Replies of this nature need no great <hi>Exercitation,</hi> and are like to afford as little <hi>ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction,</hi> unleſſe it be to ſuch as are ſo <hi>kind hearted</hi> to him, that they have before hand reſolved to believe him (or indeed any of his <hi>Bias</hi>) out of pure charity. But you will ſay, it may be, as he alleadges they were, ſo they were indeed, impertinently quoted; and what need he trouble
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:114595:3"/>himſelf with them, ſo long as they ſpeak nothing to the purpoſe? How much to the purpoſe they ſpeak, let the Reader judge, when he ſhal firſt have heard the Poſition to be prov'd, and afterward one or two in ſtead of al the reſt, ſpeaking to it in his Antagoniſts Quotation. <hi>The Author of the lawfulneſſe of obeying the preſent Government</hi> (with whom our <hi>Exercitator</hi> in the place in queſtion hath to deale) aſſerts that <hi>a Government unlawfully erected, may yet lawfully be obey'd;</hi> and the foundation upon which he builds his judgement in the Poſition, is <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. For he argues that the Apoſtle writing to the Chriſtians of that age, gives them command to be ſubject to the Powers that then were, becauſe even thoſe Powers were of God, though (as our Author conceives) they were uſurp'd Powers, being either <hi>Claudius Caeſar</hi> or <hi>Nero,</hi> both Romane Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours; from whence he concludes that <hi>unlawfull</hi> Powers in point of <hi>Title,</hi> may <hi>lawfully</hi> be obey'd; and for proofe by way of teſtimony of the godly reformed Divines con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curring in judgement with himſelf, cites <hi>Peter Martyr,</hi> page 8. in theſe words: <hi>It ſhall not here be ſcrupulouſly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Nihil hîc anxie diſputandum eſt, quo jure quâve injuriâ, principes adepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſint poteſtatem ſuam. Illud po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius agendum eſt, ut Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtratus <hi>praeſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes</hi> revereamur. Haec enrm Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtola ſcribeba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, cum Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mant jam adepti eſſent imperium orbis terrarum, quod eos <hi>per vim ſcimus</hi> oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupaſſe, &amp; poſtea Imperatores artibus nihilo melioribus rerum ſummam ad ſe pertrax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſſe. Paulus tamen ſine omni exceptione praecipit, obediendum eſſe Magiſtratilus. <hi>Per. Martyr in Rom. 13.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>by what right or by what wrong Princes have gotten their Power; this rather is to be done, that we reverence the PRE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SENT Magiſtrates; for this Epiſtle was written when the Romanes had now gotten the Empire of the world, which we KNOW they did poſſeſſe by FORCE; and that afterward, the Emperours by Policies, nothing better, drew to themſelves an univerſall Power; yet</hi> Paul <hi>doth command that Magiſtrates, without all exception, muſt be obey'd.</hi> And now let the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der judge, whither it be not ſo far from being nothing, that indeed nothing can be more to the purpoſe; for who ſees not that he aſſerts the ſelf ſame thing, and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſame ground with our <hi>Authour,</hi> without a hairs difference ſave in expreſſion? And with him doe all the reſt agree; but <hi>Bucer</hi> is more full and peremptory upon the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:114595:4"/>point,<note place="margin">Quum igitur quaeritur cui pae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rendum, non eſt ſpectandum qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis ſit qui pote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtatem exercer, nec quo jure vel injuriâ quis po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtatem inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerit, quave ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione eam admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtret, ſed tantum ſi poteſtatem haheat; ſi enim quis poteſtate pollet, jam indubitatum eſt il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum à Deo illam poteſtatem accepiſſe, unde ſine omni exceptione, illi te permittas oportet, &amp; pareas ex animo.</note> expreſſing himſelf in theſe termes: <hi>When a que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion is made whom we ſhould obey, it muſt not be lookt at what he is that exerciſes the power, or by what right or wrong he hath invaded the power, or in what manner he doth diſpenſe it, but onely if be have a power. For if any man doth excell in power, it is now out of doubt that he received that power of God. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore without all exception, thou muſt yeeld thy ſelf up to him, and heartily obey him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Tis therefore plain that the reaſon why the <hi>Exercitator</hi> makes ſuch a ſory ſhift to rid his hands of thoſe approv'd Divines, was not becauſe they ſpeak too little, but rather too much to the purpoſe; for being reſolv'd, right or wrong, to maintain his own conceit, he knew not how to decline the Authority of oppoſites ſo learned and judici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and which no judicious man but himſelf would have ſlighted, ſave by thus turning them out at the back door.</p>
               <p>But again, though this <hi>Exercitator</hi> had wanted Books, (for he ſaies he had not the Authours by him) he ſhould not have wanted reaſon for overthrowing the Reaſons that were alleadged to maintaine the Poſition of Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence which himſelf did oppoſe. The Reaſons of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuiſts, and particularly that of <hi>Salon,</hi> were at large ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed, ſo that he needed not to be at charge for Bookes to finde them, being there found to his hands. But in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed if many <hi>Exercitators</hi> were in this one, they cannot ſtand under the weight of thoſe Reaſons; and therefore he did wiſely not to take theſe Gates of <hi>Azzah</hi> on his ſhoulders, being no <hi>Sampſon,</hi> leaſt he ſhould ſinke under the weight of them. But in the meane time, till they be ſoundly anſwered, the Poſition of obedience ſtands ſtrong and unſhaken, and his Diſcourſe doth fall (with <hi>Dagon</hi>) before it.</p>
               <p>And yet our <hi>Exercitator ſuperciliouſly</hi> ſaies (and he thinks it enough, though never ſo apparently untrue, to ſay)
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:114595:4"/>
                  <hi>it reaches not the Caſe at all.</hi> But to returne to our Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citation.</p>
               <p>We are told in the Title Page, that the Diſcourſe is <hi>modeſtly and inoffenſively manag'd,</hi> (mens conſciences tell them what they ſhould do, and their works tell us what they have done) <hi>by one ſtudious of truth and peace.</hi> If he be ſo good a <hi>ſtudent,</hi> 'tis ſtrange he ſhould be ſo bad a <hi>profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient.</hi> For if we may make a better judgement of him by his <hi>works</hi> then his <hi>words,</hi> we doubt not but the Reader will finde him a very <hi>truant</hi> in the ſtudy of <hi>truth,</hi> at leaſt in the preſent controverſie, when it ſhall be brought to the Touch-ſtone. And for the <hi>peaceable and inoffenſive modeſty</hi> whereof he would beſpeak himſelf an opinion, let but the <hi>heart and deſigne</hi> of the <hi>Exercitation</hi> be compar'd with the <hi>Quotations</hi> out of <hi>Fenner</hi> and <hi>Grotius</hi> confronting his ſo candid profeſſion, and they will ſpeak him far from the pretended temper of peace and an inoffenſive modeſty. The <hi>Exercitation</hi> endeavours (though in truth by argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments no leſſe falſe then frivolous, and as injurious as ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) to fix <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpation</hi> upon the Parliament; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon decries all obedience to them, and cries up diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience as meritorious in the hearts and affections of the people: the Quotations to adde more light and heat to the buſineſſe, muſt inſinuate, <hi>That any private perſon may lawfully kill an uſurper.</hi> Though in truth he puts a dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous wrong upon the Reader, and indeed upon the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thours quoted, whilſt he racks their Tenet to ſo evil an end, and brings forth their words upon the ſtage by halves, without thoſe <hi>Cautions</hi> and <hi>Qualifications</hi> uſually annext, and requiſite to ſo tender a point, whereof we have here given a taſte.</p>
               <p>One well skill'd in Caſes of Conſcience ſaies:<note place="margin">Id curare debet occiſor ita cautè &amp; conſultò fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere, ut non pejores exitus &amp; ſcandula ex tali occiſione ſperentur. <hi>Sayr. Caſ. Conſ. lib. 7. cap. 10. n. 4.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>He that ſhall kill a Tyrant, muſt have a care that he do it with ſuch cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and wiſdom, as the killing it ſelf give not cauſe to ſeare that worſe conſequences and ſcandals may follow thereupon.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:114595:5"/>
               <p>And another of no mean eſteem for learning,<note place="margin">Tyrannus Titu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo, ut appella<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, ad tempus eſt tolerandus; omnibus autem mediis &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediis fruſtra tentaris eſt tollendus; ſed non niſi ab ordinibus five Optimatibus. <hi>Alſt. Reg. Theol. cap. 23. Artic. 8.</hi>
                  </note> and ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the <hi>Exercitator</hi> himſelf, ſaies: <hi>That a Tyrant in Title, as we call it, is to be tolerated for a time; but after all means and remedies tried in vain, is to be taken away; yet by no others then the States or chief Rulers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And to ſee the fidelity of this Exercitator; even to that very ſentence which himſelf out of the ſame Author hath cited page 74.<note place="margin">De hoc &amp;c. liceat illunn è medio tollere, ſt quidem hoc faciat Autori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate publica. <hi>Idem. Syſt. Pol. ſec. cap. 12. Reg. 4.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>De hoc</hi> &amp;c. there is annext this qualificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by him moſt in juriouſly omitted, <hi>That a private perſon in taking away a Tyrant, may not act but with publique Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Neither hath he dealt altogether faithfully with <hi>Fen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Dudl. Fenner Sacr. Theol c. <hi>13</hi> De polit. Civit. p. <hi>80.</hi>
                  </note> as he that peruſes him will finde in the place cited, whither for brevities ſake I refer him.</p>
               <p>But of all the reſt he hath moſt palpably abus'd <hi>Groti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us.</hi> For after divers qualifications and cautions both pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fixt and affixt by him, but omitted by the Exercitator, yea and ſome in the very ſentence quoted,<note place="margin">Maximè autem in re controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa judictum ſibi privatus ſumere non debet, ſed POSSESSIO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NEM ſequi. Sic tributum ſolvi Caeſari Chrtſtus jubebat, quia ejus imaginem nummus praeferebat, id eſt, quia in poſſeſſione erat imperii. <hi>Grotius, De jure pacis ac belli, lib. 1. c. 4. §. 20.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Grotius</hi> thus concludes upon the whole matter: <hi>But moſt certaine it is, that in a controverted caſe no private perſon may preſume to make himſelf a Judge, but muſt give way to POSSESSION. Thus Chriſt commanded that Tribute ſhould be paid to</hi> Caeſar, <hi>becauſe the money bore his Image, that is, becauſe he was in poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of the Empire.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And what can the meaning of the Exercitation in all this be (charity it ſelf being judge) but on the one ſide to blow the Trumpet to <hi>open Rebel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ion</hi> againſt the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of Parliament in generall? and on the other ſide to ſtrengthen the hands of <hi>private aſſaſſines</hi> againſt the lives
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:114595:5"/>of the Members in particular? And is not this modeſtly and inoffenſively manag'd? are not theſe the deſignes of one ſtudious of peace? 'Tis ſtrange the Exercitation it ſelf ſhould not bluſh, to pretend to a peaceable and inof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſive modeſty, whilſt it expoſes the blood of the Powers againſt whom it diſputes, to the luſt of every bloody miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creant. And yet the Exercitators conſcience could not but tell him, that many if not moſt of the Commons now ſitting, poſſeſſe their ſeats within thoſe walls by vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of an Election <hi>unqueſtionably,</hi> legall, and by the <hi>ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction</hi> of a Law to <hi>perpetuate</hi> them (till themſelves ſhall conſent to their own diſſolution) as <hi>unqueſtionable.</hi> And therefore he might have conſidered (for being an Exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tator, ſure he could not be ignorant) that according to that generally known, and as genarally receiv'd Maxime, <hi>In re dubia tutior eſt conditio poſſidentis;</hi> which might have taught him to forbeare ſuch unchriſtian inſinuations in an affair of ſo ſolemne and ſoveraign concernment, both in religious and civil reſpects.</p>
               <p>But we ſhall now come to particulars, and firſt to that of the <hi>pretended uſurpation,</hi> and we ſhall abſolve it in the inſuing Chapter.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> That the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpation pretended is really no <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpation.</head>
               <p>THat the Commons of <hi>England</hi> aſſembled in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſhould be charg'd with Uſurpation by any ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle perſon <hi>without doors,</hi> doubtleſſe in all reaſon cannot but ſeem very <hi>irregular;</hi> and therefore it might well have become the <hi>Exercitator</hi> (whoever he be) by that Analo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie of our Saviours words, of which he ſpeaks, <hi>pag.</hi> 3. modeſtly to have askt himſelf before he began this work, <hi>Who made him a Judge or a Rule-maker over the Commons in
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:114595:6"/>Parliament?</hi> But 'tis eaſier ſometimes to ſee a mote abroad then a beam at home. All that he ſaies to the point of U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurpation (and queſtionleſſe his zeal makes him omit no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing that he can ſay) is comprehended in the firſt Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, containing both the Charge and the grounds there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, in the inſuing deſcription of Uſurpation.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>furpation</hi> (he ſaies) <hi>is an intruſion into the ſeat of Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, a preſuming to poſſeſſe and manage the place and power thereof, without a lawfull calling, right, or title thereunto.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the proſecution of this deſcription he tels us (though with much ado about nothing) that by <hi>Authority</hi> hee means that which is <hi>ſupreme,</hi> and by a lawfull calling, <hi>a calling from the People;</hi> and this he ſaies is ſo <hi>eſſentiall</hi> to a humanely conſtituted Magiſtracy, that where it is, it makes a <hi>lawfull Magiſtracy;</hi> and the <hi>privation</hi> or want thereof makes <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpation.</hi> Again tis confeſt by himſelf, <hi>pag.</hi> 5. that by <hi>the fundamentall Government of this Nation, the Commons in Parliament have a lawfull Title to ſupremacy of power</hi> joyntly <hi>by way of</hi> coordination <hi>with the other coordinates there mentioned;</hi> and by conſequence it cannot be deny'd, <hi>that they have alſo a lawfull Title to ſupremacy of power</hi> ſeverally <hi>by way of ſupply without them.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Fuller Anſ. <hi>to D.</hi> Ferne. pag. <hi>1.</hi> Ibid. pag. <hi>6.</hi>
                  </note> For in this particular, the learned Author of the fuller anſwer to D. <hi>Ferne,</hi> will tell him that <hi>coardinata invicem ſupplent,</hi> coordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nates ſupply each other. And he gives this reaſon after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, <hi>Becauſe in a coordinate and mixt Government, one parts refuſall exempts not the other from its duty, nor muſt it defraud the whole of its ſafety; ſo it ſhould fruſtrate the very end of that its coordination, which is, ſupply for the more ſecurity of its ſafety.</hi> And he adds further in the ſame place, <hi>That in caſe of the abſence and refuſall of the other parts in coordination the ſupreme power of the whole is virtually in the part ſupplying.</hi> Neither is it materiall if it be objected; that he ſpeaks of both Houſes in the place laſt mentioned, for the reaſon in point of ſafety is the ſame whether <hi>both</hi> or but <hi>one</hi> ſupply, as was clear in the Votes againſt <hi>Hamiltons</hi> Army.</p>
               <p>From all which grounds thus apparently deduc't from our Exercitators own Doctrine, tis evident that the man is contradictory to himſelf, whilſt he endeavours to bring
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:114595:6"/>the Commons in Parliament within the compaſſe of U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurpation, as exerciſing the Supreme Power without a lawfull calling; whereas himſelf hath plainly confeſt that by way of coordination <hi>joyntly,</hi> and therefore <hi>ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally</hi> alſo by way of ſupply, they have a lawfull calling to the exerciſe of the Supreme Power. Whats objected to evade this palpable contradiction? Tis alleadg'd, <hi>That the Commons now ſitting are not a Houſe,</hi> and that's the onely <hi>ſubterfuge,</hi> the old and thredbare <hi>ſhift</hi> of the late Kings Party, of which if we can but uncaſe him, we ſhall allow him (beſides the whole crowd of his other impertinencies) the <hi>Apex, Zenith,</hi> and <hi>Culmen</hi> of his high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flown Rhetorick, with all the <hi>Poetica licentia</hi> of his tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gicall <hi>American ſcene;</hi> for we muſt acknowledge he were an Exercitator that deſerv'd richly to be whipt, if he could not with ſome little handſomneſſe at leaſt, ſo tell his own tale, as to make it ſerve his own turn.</p>
               <p>Firſt therefore if they be no houſe, we would willingly know how they came to be none. We well know that once they were a Houſe, and we know as well how they came to be a Houſe; in a word, by a lawfull calling from the People (to uſe his owne expreſſion) to <hi>conſtitute</hi> them, and the ſanction of a Law to <hi>continue</hi> them a Houſe, till their own <hi>conſent</hi> ſhould diſſolve them; which till them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ſhall have declared to be paſt, we cannot eaſily be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve any other that ſhall tell us of their diſſolution. Yea but they are no Houſe, for he ſaies <hi>they are under a force,</hi> and he proves it out of all cry, becauſe they are <hi>willing</hi> and <hi>conſenting</hi> to that force. Now in truth they deſerve to be pitti'd. What to be conſtrain'd to act againſt their wils with all their hearts!<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Ariſt. Ethic. lib. <hi>3.</hi> cap. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> I dare ſay tis ſuch a force as never men were under before them. He talks of an <hi>uſu-pation,</hi> but I am ſure here's a <hi>contradiction</hi> to the <hi>life.</hi> But beſides the contradiction, how knows he they were conſenting? did they ever tell him ſo? I am ſure they have told the world the contrary, as appears by their Meſſage to the Generall and Councell of Warre. It will be ſaid, that was but a meere formality; and, if they did not conſent
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:114595:7"/>to the force, why did they not proſecute the Authors of it? I anſwer, By denying the conſequence; neither can the Exercitator, were he as able as his admirers do or poſſibly can imagine him, ever prove, That to forbeare the proſecution <hi>ad ſummum jus</hi> of the Authors, is to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to the evil of an act. For inſtance, If a man remit a wilfull treſpaſſe, that will beare action in Law to his Neighbour, doth he conſent to the evil of that act? or to come a little nearer both to the Exercitator and the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent caſe: When the Apprentices made a force upon the Houſe, it was afterward mov'd in the Houſe, whereof Mr. <hi>Pelham</hi> ſate Speaker, That the Authors of that force might be proſecuted, and carried in the <hi>negative,</hi> will the Exercitator ſay that the Houſe then ſitting was there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore conſenting to the force, and conſequently was not a Houſe? I am confident he loves them too well to think ſo. Yet, <hi>Aut haec cum illis ſunt habenda, aut illa cum his a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittenda ſunt,</hi> either he muſt <hi>grant</hi> that the Houſe then ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting was conſenting to the force then, and therefore was not a Houſe, or <hi>deny</hi> that the Houſe now ſitting is <hi>conſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> to the force which is urg'd, and ſo conclude that <hi>they are ſtill a Houſe,</hi> notwithſtanding the <hi>non-proſecution</hi> of the Authors of that force. But to help both him and his friends out of this difficulty, who may not perceive that wil, that tis one thing to <hi>paſſe by,</hi> and another thing to <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent</hi> to a miſcarriage; the latter may not be done upon <hi>any</hi> conſideration whatſoever; the former not onely may, but muſt be done upon <hi>many,</hi> when the Reaſon of the State (which our Author ſaies,<note place="margin">Fuller Anſ. pag. <hi>25.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>the Law makes to reſidein both Houſes joyntly by way of coordination, and ſeverally by way of ſupply</hi>) ſhall think it fit. And <hi>in this finall reſolution of the States judgment the people</hi> (he ſaies) <hi>are to reſt.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ibid. pag. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> But to give an unqueſtion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able warrant to this diſtinction and the practice of the Houſe of Commons upon it,<note place="margin">Mica 7.18.</note> tis ſaid of God himſelfe, that <hi>he paſſes by the tranſgreſſions of the remnant of his people,</hi> and yet it were blaſphemy to ſay that he is in the leaſt <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting</hi> to them;<note place="margin">The Reader is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſir'd <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> notice that the miſca iage here pretended is only ſuppoſd not granted.</note> and can there be a better preſident to warrant the Commons paſſing by a miſcarriage (with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:114595:7"/>out being guilty of conſenting to it) rather then by cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling for a ſtrict account to ſacrifice the <hi>peace and ſafety</hi> of the Commonwealth upon the ſervice of thoſe <hi>Priviledges,</hi> which no man that hath his reaſon and a freedom to uſe it can deny to be intended in their own <hi>nature</hi> and by their firſt <hi>inſtitution</hi> to be <hi>fences</hi> and <hi>ornaments</hi> for the <hi>good</hi> of the Common-wealth, not <hi>firebrands</hi> of contention for its <hi>ruine? Priviledges</hi> are <hi>ſervants</hi> to the good of the publike, not <hi>Lords</hi> over it, and therefore are to be <hi>reſpected</hi> in order to the publike good, and in order to the publike good are to be <hi>neglected,</hi> according as the Commons in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment (whoſe they are, either to <hi>uſe</hi> or <hi>not uſe,</hi> and who in ſuch caſes as concerne their own priviledges, are the only competent Judges) ſhall determine. Yea but for all this,<note place="margin">As they have with common approbation laid them aſide in giving way that Members ſhall be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to the ſuits of Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditors.</note> he ſaies that <hi>the Houſe muſt be free for all to come to, that their acts may be free and authoritative.</hi> If he mean a freedom in reſpect of any <hi>Vote</hi> paſt within doors, to exclude ſuch as ſhall not conforme to the Orders of the Houſe, nothing can be more apparently untrue; for the Houſe, as tis well known, paſt ſeverall Votes to exclude thoſe that would not engage in the <hi>Vow and Covenant</hi> concerning the Lord Generall <hi>Eſſex;</hi> and upon the Votes for the taking of <hi>the Selemn League and Covenant,</hi> divers that before had ſate in the Houſe, were actually excluded for refuſall. Yet I never heard of any, no not of the perſons excluded, that thereupon deny'd the <hi>being</hi> and <hi>Authority</hi> of the Houſe. It is therefore unqueſtionable, that the Commons in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment have a power to exclude ſuch of their Members as ſhall not conform to the Votes and Orders of that Houſe, and yet neither themſelves be ever the leſſe <hi>free,</hi> nor their acts any whit the leſſe <hi>authoritative.</hi> But ſecondly, if he mean that all the Members muſt be free in reſpect of any reſtraint, ſave what is put upon them by the Votes and Authority of the Houſe; tis abſolutely anſwered ſo, they are; and let the Exercitator or any of his judgement prove the contrary if they can. Again, let it be granted that divers of the Members were ſometimes under a force, can that hinder thoſe from ſitting and being a Houſe,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:114595:8"/>who never were either <hi>under</hi> or <hi>conſenting</hi> to that force? If it could, tis deſired the Exercitator would ſhew how the Commons were a Houſe, and their Acts authorita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, when the late King had divers of their Members in <hi>priſon</hi> in his Quarters; for by his Doctrine if <hi>one</hi> Member be under a force, it <hi>nulls</hi> the Authority of the Houſe. But who, unleſſe he wilfully ſhut his eyes, canuot ſee the mountainous groſſeneſſe of theſe abſurdities? Wherefore to conclude this particular,<note place="margin">Fuller Anſ. pag. <hi>7.</hi>
                  </note> our Author in this caſe will tell him, <hi>That an injury cannot take away a right;</hi> which though in truth it never can, yet according to our Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citators principles it muſt, if a force upon ſome of the Members could hinder the reſt from being a Houſe. Laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, tis objected by the Exercitator, That the Commons now ſitting <hi>are not the major part.</hi> And tis anſwered, What is that to the purpoſe, ſo long as they are a Houſe? what if the major part of the Commons had deſerted their truſt, and gone to the late King, ſhould that have hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd thoſe that had ſtaid behinde and continued faithfull to their truſt, from being a Houſe? The contrary is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent in the Lords, who while they ſate, were never lookt on as being ever the leſſe a Houſe becauſe the <hi>greater</hi> part deſerted them, and were afterward juſtly excluded the Houſe by the far <hi>leſſer</hi> number of Lords ſitting.</p>
               <p>To conclude, the Exercitator acknowledges <hi>pag.</hi> 7. that if it could be made good, that the whole Nation had in the originall conſtitution of Government com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted the ſole power to the Houſe of Commons, there could be no Uſurpation. Now it is as apparent as the light by his own grounds, that the whole Nation (for the Lords if they fall not under a <hi>Nationall,</hi> muſt fall un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a <hi>perſonall</hi> conſideration) hath committed the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme power to the Houſe of Commons <hi>joyntly,</hi> by way of coordination, and <hi>ſolely</hi> by way of ſupply; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore by his own confeſſion, they can never be concluded under uſurpation, as exerciſing that power without a lawfull calling, for the exerciſe whereof they have by his own grounds a lawfull calling from the People.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:114595:8"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> That the Oathes objected oblige not againſt obedience to the preſent Government.</head>
               <p>THe Aſſertion that we are now to make good againſt the Exercitator, is, <hi>That the Oathes by him objected obliges not againſt obedience to the preſent Powers.</hi> To demonſtrate this truth with as much brevity as perſpicuity, we ſhall firſt lay down certaine generally receiv'd principles, by which as by ſo many rules, we may evidently diſcerne in what caſes, <hi>ex confeſſo,</hi> Oaths do not oblige. Secondly, we ſhall examine and anſwer our <hi>Exercitators</hi> objections, why thoſe Rules ſhould not take place in the Oaths in controverſie. And a main reaſon inducing to the choyce of this method, is, becauſe truth and experience joyntly tells us, that of commenting on words and ſentences in controverted Oaths there can never be an end. For the fancy of man being of ſo various a working, and work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a variety, hardly can that word or ſentence be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded, which it will not ſcrve and wier-draw to its owne ſenſe, if it have not ſome clear and conſtant prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of truth, as a bright but unerring ſtar, both to guide and fix it.</p>
               <p>In the firſt place therefore 'tis generally granted, as a Principle of truth that cannot be deny'd,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dr. Sanders, Pral. 2. §. 11.</hi> Juramentum non tollit obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gationem prie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem.</note> 
                  <hi>That no Oath can ſo oblige, as to take away the obligation of a former duty.</hi> The force by which all Oaths are ſaid to binde, is <hi>conſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive</hi> onely, never <hi>deſtructive;</hi> they may impoſe a Duty where they finde none, or diſpoſe of certain circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces about the performance, but they cannot deſtroy or <hi>take away</hi> a duty where they finde it.</p>
               <p>As much with as much clearneſſe may be ſaid concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Oaths in controverſle, and objected to obſtruct
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:114595:9"/>our obedience to the preſent Government. Tis moſt true, they had a <hi>conſtructive</hi> force to oblige according to their ſeverall <hi>limitations,</hi> to the former Government whilſt it did <hi>obtain;</hi> but as true it is, they never had, nor ever can have a <hi>deſtructive</hi> force to oblige to diſobedience, and diſoblige from obedience to all other Governments in the future actually obtaining. For tis evident, that by ſuch a <hi>deſtructive</hi> force they ſhould (which tis confeſt they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not) <hi>take away</hi> the obligation of: a <hi>former duty,</hi> ſeeing we are firſt bound to obey <hi>all Government in gener all</hi> as the <hi>Ordinance of Ged,</hi> and ſo by a <hi>Divine right;</hi> before we are bound to obey any <hi>forme</hi> of Government in particular, which is but the <hi>Ordinance of man,</hi> and ſo onely by a <hi>hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane right.</hi> Tis obſervable, that the reaſon given why no Oath can take away the obligation of a former duty, is, becauſe an <hi>inferiour act</hi> of the perſon in <hi>duty</hi> oblig'd, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not take away the <hi>ſuperiour right</hi> of the perſon to whom the obligation is <hi>due.</hi> How much leſſe then can an infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour act of the <hi>Creature</hi> obliging himſelf by the Oaths in controverſie, take away not the Superiour but <hi>Supreme Right</hi> of the Creator, by virtue of which he ſtood obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to God in <hi>duty</hi> to give obedience to all Government in generall, before he obliged himſelf to man to give obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to the then obtaining <hi>forme</hi> of Government in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular? Yet this <hi>Supreme Right</hi> of God, and the obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of duty in point of obedience to all Government in generall by virtue of that Right, muſt actually be <hi>taken away,</hi> if upon the removall of the former Government and ſubſtitution of another in its ſtead, and both by that Divine hand which may and doth at pleaſure diſpoſe of all Governments, the Oaths objected oblige againſt O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, and inforce a non-ſubjection to the <hi>hand</hi> of God in the preceding change, and the <hi>Ordinance</hi> of God in the preſent Government. For whilſt they ſtill oblige to be ſubject to the Government that was but <hi>is not,</hi> and not to be ſubject to the Government that is, they indeed oblige to be ſubject to <hi>no Government,</hi> and conſequently to <hi>Anarchy</hi> and confuſion. But ſuch an Obligation muſt
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:114595:9"/>needs be Null, becauſe as is evident from all that hath beene ſaid, unlawfull and wicked.</p>
               <p>Whats objected here by our Exercitator? he tells us page 46. <hi>All Authority hangs not upon the backe of Vſurpati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> ſo he termes the preſent Government, and ſaies <hi>this</hi> [the preſent Government] <hi>may come downe, and that</hi> [the former) <hi>recover it ſelfe and ſtand upright.</hi> To which we anſwer. Firſt, It hath already been ſhewed that if he have not contradicted the truth in his deſcription of Vſurpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, p. 1. he hath contradicted both himſelfe and the Truth, in the Application of it to the preſent Powers. To which we ſhall onely adde, that among coordinate ſtates and compeeres ſuch as he hath confeſt, page 5. the preſent to have beene, there can be no advantage of right in point of Title, ſave what ariſes from the advantage of a <hi>better cauſe,</hi> the one ſide <hi>faithfully</hi> endeavouring accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to truſt, the <hi>ſafety,</hi> and proſperity of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth; the other <hi>faithleſly</hi> betraying truſt and endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring its <hi>ruine and deſtruction;</hi> in which caſe the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Tenet is, that the juſt party hath <hi>ſufficient</hi> Title enough to ſave the Commonwealth, but the unjuſt <hi>none</hi> to deſtroy it, and therefore may juſtly be depoſ'd and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſht by the other coordinate in ſupremacy of Power. And certainly if in giving a Right judgement of the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits of the preſent Cauſe, the <hi>intereſt</hi> of the <hi>reformed Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion</hi> and the <hi>publique liberties</hi> of the Nation muſt (as what elſe muſt) by <hi>honeſt men</hi> be regarded, it cannot in reaſon be doubted, but al ſuch wil unanimouſly conclude, if the houre of temptation be not upon them, that the preſent powers haue ſo farre the advantage of a better Cauſe, as the Cauſe of <hi>Chriſt</hi> is better then <hi>Antichriſts,</hi> and the cauſe of <hi>Common liberty</hi> better then that of <hi>Tyranny.</hi> Neither is it probable that they will ever finde Cauſe to reienquiſh their judgements in this particular, untill our Exeroitator by a ſecond and more ſound Exercitation ſhall upon <hi>infallible</hi> evidence ſubſtantially and to <hi>ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction</hi> demonſtrate, that the bloody &amp; idolatrous <hi>Iriſh,</hi> are the beſt and moſt cordiall inſtruments to carry on the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:114595:10"/>worke of Reformation, and the intereſt of the <hi>true refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Religion;</hi> that prerogative Court-paraſites are the <hi>trueſt</hi> Patriots and <hi>propereſt</hi> champions of the <hi>publique li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty</hi> of the Nation; and in a word that Hamiltons Army howeverdiſclaim'd by the Kirk, and all the truly religious of Scotland, invaded this Nation out of pure <hi>Zeale</hi> to the ends of the <hi>Covenant,</hi> and the intereſt of all truly religious Covenanters,</p>
               <q>At<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> idem iungat vulpes &amp; mulgeat Hircos.</q>
               <p>But ſecondly, to doe our Exercitator a courteſie let it be ſuppoſed (becauſe he will needs have it ſo) that the pretended uſurpation is reall; what then? will he then maintaine his ground any better, when he ſhall lie at his own guard &amp; have the advantage to chooſe his own wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon? Let the Reader judge, <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpation</hi> (he ſaies) <hi>may ſhortly fall.</hi> It may? yes, and it <hi>may not;</hi> it may not fall <hi>ſhortly,</hi> not a <hi>long</hi> time, many <hi>yeares, ages, never;</hi> what then? certainly then either all authority muſt hang on the backe of that which he is pleaſed to cal V ſurpation, or elſe it muſt all fall to the ground. For by the [may be] of our Exercitators Doctrine, there not only is no authoritie in England at preſent, but neither himſelfe nor any man elſe knowes, whither ever there will be any to the worlds end. And what is this but by one daſh of a ridiculous [may be] to ſubvert the Ordinance of God in Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and the Order of Mankinde in obedience to it? The <hi>fuller Anſwer,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Fuller Anſ. pag. <hi>3.</hi>
                  </note> will teach him a better leſſen, who according to the truth tells us, <hi>that there be in all ſocietyes of men</hi> (and thereſore in the preſent amongſt us) <hi>a go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment capable of its end, ſafety, is out of queſtion Gods in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution and morall.</hi> Nay indeed he might have taught himſelfe a better leſſon; for whileſt hee defines Vſurpati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>a preſuming to poſſeſſe the ſeat, and manage the power of the ſupreame Authority,</hi> he acknowledges even under Vſurpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion a <hi>ſeat</hi> fixt, and an <hi>actuall</hi> Exerciſe of the ſupreame Authority, by the fixure of which Seat we ſee the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:114595:10"/>at preſent eſtabliſht in <hi>Order,</hi> and by the influence of which <hi>Authority,</hi> publique juſtice is fully adminiſtred, both which being the ordinance of God, can no more be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away by any <hi>act</hi> or <hi>oath</hi> of man, then it could at firſt have beene <hi>inſtituted</hi> by any other then a divine wiſedom, or could ſince have beene <hi>conſtantly</hi> maintained, otherwiſe, then by the <hi>powerfull,</hi> though <hi>ſecret</hi> influence of a Divine and Almighty hand.</p>
               <p>And therefore we doubt not but to make it evident as the Day, that however the Exercitator <hi>preſume</hi> to make him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe an accuſer of others for <hi>preſuming</hi> to the ſeat of Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, there cannot eaſily be found a more <hi>preſumptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Vſurpation,</hi> then that whereof he ſtands guilty, and obnoxious both to God and man. For whereas he char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges moſt untruly, and therefore moſt ungratefully, thoſe to whom he owes his <hi>protection,</hi> with <hi>preſuming</hi> to the ſeat of Authority, himſelf, which is infinetely worſe, <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumes</hi> to overthrow the very <hi>ſeat</hi> of Authority, and fling the <hi>Authority it ſelfe</hi> wholly out of the Nation, ſo at once endeavouring to make void the <hi>ſupreame Ordinance</hi> of God, for the Civil welfaire of man-kinde, and leave the Nation withont all <hi>Order</hi> or <hi>Government</hi> to be ſwallowed up of <hi>Anarchy</hi> and <hi>confuſion,</hi> and in this moſt miſerable eſtate muſt the Nation by his <hi>irreligious</hi> [may be] continue even to the worlds end, unleſſe the publique enemy for whom he pleades, and upon whoſe backe he makes all authority to hang, ſhall be pleaſed to give leave that Gods Ordinance of Government may againe take place among us.</p>
               <p>For the ſecond, to anſwer him out of his own definiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Uſurpation: Firſt, we muſt diſtinguiſh between the <hi>Act</hi> of Intruſion, and the <hi>Perſon</hi> that makes the Intruſion; Its granted that the <hi>Act</hi> of Intruſion is not the <hi>Ordinance</hi> of God; but the <hi>Perſon</hi> of the intruder conſidered <hi>per ſe,</hi> and in <hi>actuall poſſeſsion</hi> of the ſupreame power, not onely may be, but certainely is the Ordinance of God; whilſt by God he is put into a capacity of being a <hi>Miniſter</hi> (and accordingly acts) <hi>for the good</hi> of thoſe over whom the hand of God hath exalted him in place of higher power; although it be but for a time, and onely by way of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:114595:11"/>otherwiſe there muſt neceſſarily be a <hi>breach</hi> in that Golden Chaine of <hi>Order</hi> and <hi>Government</hi> which God hath <hi>ordained,</hi> to binde up man-kinde, from <hi>inevitably,</hi> and by our Exercitators [may be] <hi>irrecoverably</hi> falling into Anarchy and confuſion upon <hi>every concuſſion</hi> of State, and the <hi>frequent</hi> Revolutions of Governours and Governments, of which our own Nation hath not had the leaſt experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. And upon thoſe grounds we even now mention'd, tis, that even they that allow a removall of a Perſon in po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer without a Title, allow it onely in an <hi>orderly</hi> way, and in <hi>cleare</hi> and <hi>untroverted</hi> caſes, and <hi>unquestionably</hi> condu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing to the good of the Common-Wealth. Againe we muſt diſtinguiſh between the <hi>Act</hi> of Intruſion, and the <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority</hi> or Supreame power; the former as was granted, before, is not, but the latter <hi>ever</hi> is the Ordinance of God. For the <hi>Seat</hi> of authority being from the beginning, fix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the hand of the moſt High; the <hi>authority</hi> or ſupream Power annex'd to, and iſſuing out of that <hi>Seat,</hi> can never ceaſe to be the Ordinance of God, by what hand ſoever he is pleaſed to diſpence it, who may, and doth diſpence it by what hand he pleaſes; and therefore it may not be <hi>reſiſted</hi> in the hand of any whom himſelfe hath put in <hi>poſſeſſion,</hi> though by meanes <hi>extraordinary</hi> to us, without ſin, and incurring the danger of receiving the damnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on threatned by the Apoſtle, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.2. Neither can the Obligation of any Oath whatſoever, either <hi>invalidate</hi> a Duty, or <hi>inforce</hi> a ſin in this particular.</p>
               <p>But to come to a ſecond principle, It's a rule beyond all exception,<note place="margin">Indubijs ſequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum eſt partem tutiorem <hi>D. Sands. Prael. 2. § 9.</hi>
                  </note> that <hi>indoubtfull caſes the ſafer part is to be cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen.</hi> The doubt of which we are now ſpeaking, may be either concerning the <hi>Explication,</hi> or the <hi>Obligation</hi> of an Oath; and that part is in all doubts out of all contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie the <hi>ſafer,</hi> which hath <hi>nothing</hi> of <hi>Sin,</hi> and <hi>moſt</hi> of <hi>Duty</hi> in it. The preſent doubt concerning the Oathes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverted, reſpects their <hi>Obligation,</hi> whether ſuch as may juſtly hinder obedience to the preſent Government; and it hath been aſſerted againſt the Exercitator, that the <hi>ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer part</hi> as including nothing of <hi>Sin,</hi> and moſt of <hi>Duty,</hi> is
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:114595:11"/>the <hi>Negative;</hi> that the Oathes objected, neither do nor can bind againſt obedience to the preſent Government. The reaſon is, becauſe its a <hi>ſin</hi> againſt the <hi>fifth Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> implicitely, and expreſſely againſt <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.1. to be under <hi>no Government;</hi> its conſequently a <hi>neceſſary Duty</hi> to be under <hi>ſome,</hi> and no <hi>ſin</hi> to be under <hi>any,</hi> becauſe all Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment is the <hi>Ordinance</hi> of God, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.1. If there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Oathes in controverſie ſhould oblige againſt obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to the preſent Government, they ſhould binde from a neceſſary <hi>Duty,</hi> to a manifeſt <hi>Sin;</hi> but nothing can oblige unto <hi>Sinne,</hi> and therefore no Oath whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever.</p>
               <p n="2">2ly. If it be true that in doubtfull caſes the <hi>ſafer part</hi> is to be choſen, tis as true that in all ſuch caſes,<note place="margin">In re dubia turi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or eſt pars poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidentis.</note> the <hi>party in poſſeſſion</hi> is the <hi>ſafter part.</hi> But that which in the preſent Contorverſie, puts the doubt out of all doubt, is that the <hi>party in poſſeſſion</hi> have ever had at leaſt an equall Title, as coordinates (<hi>ex confeſſo</hi>) with their <hi>Competitors.</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore at preſent have a ſuperiour, or rather indeed the <hi>on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> Title, in regard of the juſtneſs of their owne, and the unjuſtneſs of the adverſe parties cauſe, unleſſe (as was ſaid before) a confederacy with the bloody Iriſh, and Hamil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tons <hi>invaſive</hi> Army muſt be juſtin'd as the <hi>juſter</hi> cauſe, and withall, as the <hi>ſafer part.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What evaſion hath our Exercitator here to extricate himſelfe out of this difficulty? His old <hi>Tenedian</hi> axe ſtill.<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> Vid Eraſin. Chiliad.</note> Firſt, the <hi>pretended</hi> Uſurpation, and then that <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpation is not the Ordinance of God.</hi> For the firſt we have anſwered it once and again in the preceding part of this diſcourſe; neither ſhall we write after his Copy, in his frequent and tireſome Tautologies; it were too great an affliction to the Reader to vexe him, <hi>uſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ad nauſeam,</hi> with his <hi>Crambe his millies <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>cta.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But the full proſecution of this will be proper in the third aſſertion.</p>
               <p>We come now to a third principle,<note place="margin">In juramento ſemper jus ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perioris intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitur exceptum. <hi>2 Decret. 24 19</hi>
                  </note> and it ſpeakes as the reſt <hi>ex confeſſo,</hi> (for we intend ſuch onely) thus. <hi>In all Oathes whatſoever the ſuperiours right over the inferiour, is ever
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:114595:12"/>underſtood to ſtand excepted, as that which can never fall under their Obligation.</hi> Or (it may be) more plainely thus, No Oath of an <hi>inferiour,</hi> can binde againſt that <hi>Right</hi> of a <hi>Superiour,</hi> by which he hath a <hi>lawfull Power</hi> over him.</p>
               <p>There are two <hi>Superiours,</hi> or rather indeed <hi>Suprems,</hi> that have a lawfull power over all men, by vertue of a <hi>Supreame Right,</hi> againſt which no Oath can oblige; in a word, <hi>God</hi> and the Common-Wealth. This <hi>Right</hi> of God to begin with it in the firſt place, is not onely <hi>ſupreame,</hi> but <hi>abſolute,</hi> and therewithall univerſall, and extends over all men, in all things, by vertue whereof he claimes a <hi>lawfull power,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Job. 33.13.</note> at pleaſure to diſpoſe of all, rendering no man an account of his wayes; but certainely of all that he claimes a power to diſpoſe, there is nothing wherein he is more peremptory, there is nothing which with a more high hand under the name of the Moſt high, he aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerts unto himſelf with a more ſoveraigne majeſty and <hi>abſolute</hi> ſoverainty, then the ſwaying ſtroake in the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Men,<note place="margin">Dan. <hi>4.17.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> Hwnillimum ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minem. <hi>Hier.</hi>
                  </note> and an undoubted right to give it to whomſoever he will, and ſet up over it the <hi>humbleſt</hi> of men. When therefore the moſt High actually puts downe one, and ſets up another Power, and ſo by vertue of his ſupreame abſolute, and univerſall Right gives the Kingdome to whomſoever, <hi>HE,</hi> not <hi>WEE</hi> will, (for ſuch a contra-diſtinction the ſolmne inforcement of the words, muſt of neceſſity inferre in the eye of any impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall judge;) who can plead a Right againſt God? or what Oath ſtand valid to <hi>invalidate</hi> his <hi>Right?</hi> Eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally ſeeing all <hi>inferiour</hi> Rights ceaſe and determine (at leaſt <hi>pro tempore</hi>) upon the <hi>actuall</hi> entrance, and inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of the <hi>Superiour;</hi> how much more ſhall the <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour</hi> right of man be <hi>no right,</hi> when not a <hi>Superiour</hi> on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, which yet it ſelfe might be ſubordinate and doubtfull, but the ſupreame abſolute and undoubted right of God, by an <hi>actuall</hi> and <hi>powerfull</hi> interpoſition <hi>takes place?</hi> 'Tis ſaid,<note place="margin">Si filius fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lias jurel ſe fac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turum aliquid in ſelicitum; pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter autem rei</note> that in caſe a Sonne being under his Fathers power, ſhall oblige himſelfe by an Oath, to an Act in it ſelfe law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full;
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:114595:12"/>and the Father being ignorant of the thing,<note place="margin">ignorus aliud ei faciendum im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peret, quod impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diat id fieri quod juratum eſt, filius non tenetur jura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mento: quia lege divina na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turali tenerur parere imperio patris <hi>D. Sands Pral. 2. § 10.</hi>
                  </note> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand ſomewhat elſe to bee done, that hinders the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhment of what was ſworne; the Oath of the Son is not obliging; becauſe by the law of God and Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, he is bound to obey his Father. How much more then are the Sonnes of men oblig'd to <hi>obey</hi> the God both of that <hi>Law</hi> and <hi>Nature,</hi> the <hi>everlaſting Father,</hi> by ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection to the powers that are, becauſe they are Ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of him: and how much leſſe can any Oath binde againſt Obedience to him by ſuch ſubjection? Seeing all Oathes at their firſt taking, are to take in the <hi>tacite</hi> condition of a <hi>ſalva potestate juperioris,</hi> an exemption of the <hi>Superiours</hi> Right, much more of the Right of the moſt high, by a <hi>ſi deus permiſerit,</hi> if God ſay <hi>a men</hi> to the Oath taken.</p>
               <p>What ſayes our Exercitator to all this? <hi>God gives no power to <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpers</hi> he ſayes; but ſurely tis ſafer to ſay with <hi>truth</hi> it ſelfe, <hi>Joh.</hi> 18.11. They could have <hi>no power</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe he <hi>gave</hi> it them. And tis certaine that our Saviour there ſpeakes of a <hi>juriciall</hi> Power, and to a Perſon that was an <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurper,</hi> if ever yet there were any. For our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour himſelfe (if we will receive the truth out of God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and judicious Mr. <hi>Perkins</hi> mouth) was the true heire,<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Perkins</hi> Expoſ. on the Epiſtle of <hi>Jude.</hi>
                     </note> and had the onely title of Right to the Crowne and Kingdome of the Jewes. Beſides, he muſt either contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict himſelfe, and there-withall confeſſe the truth, or the Scripture in <hi>expreſs termes,</hi> and therin given his own opinion the fall, whilſt he denyes that God <hi>gives</hi> the Kingdome to <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpers,</hi> whoſe tis to <hi>give</hi> to whomſoever he will. For he nndertakes to prove <hi>Jereboam</hi> an Uſurper, <hi>page</hi> 1. and yet he is not aſham'd there to quote 1 <hi>King.</hi> 11. where at verſe 31. The Lord the God of Iſrael ſayes, <hi>Behold I wil rend the Kingdom out of theh and of</hi> Solomon, <hi>and GI<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>e ten Tribes unto thee.</hi> But our Exercitator not without manifeſt wrong to the <hi>expreſſe</hi> Text ſayes; <hi>yea ſuppoſe it a grant,</hi> As if when God had in termes ſaid to <hi>Jeroboam, I will give;</hi> there were not ſufficient ground from the ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility</hi> of every word that proceeds out of the mouth of
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:114595:13"/>God, <hi>abſolutely</hi> to conclude a <hi>full Grant.</hi> But wee ſhall not here anticipate that which wee intend hereafter more fully to diſcuſſe for the further confirmation of this par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, when wee ſhall come to the third aſſertion, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for the preſent we muſt ſtill referre the Reader. Only for a concluſion, take the late judgement of our owne Divines, with learned Mr. <hi>Diodati</hi>'s concurrent in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to the preſent Objection, in theſe words on <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ordained of God, that is inſtituted of God among man-kinde, to Rule and Governe men in Order as in Gods ſtead. For God is the Author of this Order in the world: and all thoſe which attaine unto this equity or excellency, doe attaine unto it either by his manifeſt will and approbation, when the meanes are juſt and lawfull, or elſe by his ſecret providence, with permiſsion and toleration, when the meanes are unlawfull: and it is juſt and equall that man ſhould approve and tolerate that which God himſelfe approves and tolerates: and that he approves and tolerates, which wee cannot by any lawfull meanes apointed by him decline and avoid. All therefore who reſiſt authority, make war after a ſort with god himſelfe.</hi> Ann. on Rom. 13.1. Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dati. ibid.</p>
               <p>A Second <hi>Superiour,</hi> or to ſpeake more properly, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong things of an inferiour ranke under the moſt high, <hi>Supreame,</hi> for <hi>ſalus populi ſuprema lex,</hi> is the <hi>Common-wealth, bonum publicum.</hi> Againſt the <hi>ſoveraigne</hi> Right of this; <hi>ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour,</hi> and that lawfull power which it hath over us, no Oath can oblige, and conſequently not the Oathes pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended. This is no deny'd by the Exercitator himſelfe. For ſpeaking to this Argument urged againſt the Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of the preſent Oathes, by the Author of <hi>the law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe of obeying &amp;c.</hi> He grants page 44. <hi>If the thing ſworn ſhall become privative of, or oppoſite to the publike good, or wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>being of the Nation in its owne nature and neceſſarily, the Oath would be void; for to a ſinfull thing there can be no Obligation.</hi> But to aſſume upon his owne conceſſion in the premiſes, moſt certaine it is, that where Order and good Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, publike juſtice, and peace may be had, and ſurely
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:114595:13"/>it may be, nay it is generally had under the preſent Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, witneſſe all the publike ſeates of Juſtice in the Land, there to reſiſt the powers adminiſtring this <hi>Order</hi> and <hi>Government,</hi> publike <hi>Juſtice</hi> and <hi>Peace,</hi> is as much in its owne <hi>nature,</hi> and as <hi>neceſſarily deſtructive</hi> to the <hi>publike good</hi> and <hi>wel-being</hi> of the Nation, as <hi>diſorder</hi> and <hi>Anarehy</hi> is to <hi>Order,</hi> and <hi>Government,</hi> or <hi>war</hi> and <hi>conſuſion</hi> to pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like <hi>Juſtice</hi> and <hi>Peace;</hi> in a word, as much in its owne <hi>na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> and as <hi>neceſſarily privative</hi> of, and <hi>oppoſite</hi> to the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like <hi>good</hi> and <hi>wel-being</hi> of the Nation, as the <hi>privation</hi> of, and <hi>oppoſition</hi> to the proper immediate and neceſſary <hi>meanes</hi> is in its owne <hi>nature,</hi> and <hi>neceſſarily privative</hi> of, and <hi>oppoſite</hi> to the <hi>end</hi> it ſelfe. Whereupon it follows evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently and undeniably, that to ſuch a <hi>ſinfull reſiſtance</hi> of the Powers adminiſtring, there can be no Obligation; and conſequently the Oathes objected in that reſpect are <hi>void</hi> by our Exercitators own <hi>conceſſion.</hi> And to evince this yet more fully (if at leaſt there can be a fuller evicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) from his owne principles and expreſions. <hi>We ſay on all hands</hi> ſayes our Exercitator) page 33. <hi>The King it for the Kingdome, as the meanes is for the end;</hi> and the ſame in effect we have from the mouth of a King, <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing,</hi> and therewithall <hi>confirming</hi> this truth as a <hi>Royall Law,</hi> that the <hi>King</hi> is for the <hi>Common-wealth,</hi> and not the <hi>Common-wealth</hi> for the <hi>King;</hi> which granted,<note place="margin">King James.</note> if <hi>Oathes</hi> and <hi>Duties</hi> (doe, as indeed they muſt) oblige to reſpect things concern'd, according to their owne <hi>ranke</hi> and <hi>dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity;</hi> and the rule hold alwaies true, as indeed it can never faile, that <hi>finis quo ultimatior co influxu potentior,</hi> the higheſt <hi>end</hi> hath the ſtrongeſt <hi>influence;</hi> and to that <hi>end,</hi> (as our Fuller Anſwer very fully) <hi>ſtill all other ſubordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate ends ſtand but in the Office of meanes;</hi> 'tis cleare that as both the <hi>Oathes</hi> were for the <hi>King,</hi> and both <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Oathes</hi> for the <hi>Common-wealth,</hi> as ſubordinate <hi>meanes</hi> for the ultimate <hi>End;</hi> ſo both the one and the other oblige onely as <hi>condueing,</hi> but neither the one nor the other can oblige as <hi>deſtructive</hi> to the <hi>Common-wealth,</hi> or <hi>bonum pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licum;</hi> for ſo the nature of the <hi>meanes,</hi> ſhould be to <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroy</hi>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:114595:14"/>the <hi>End,</hi> which is a contradiction in nature, ſeeing the very <hi>eſſence</hi> and <hi>intrinſecall forme</hi> of the <hi>meanes,</hi> conſiſts in this that they are <hi>apra nata ad finent,</hi> naturally <hi>conducing</hi> to the <hi>End,</hi> elſe they are but <hi>equivocally</hi> tearm'd <hi>meanes.</hi> In ſumme then, we already have the <hi>meanes</hi> ſufficient (by experience) to the <hi>End;</hi> we have the <hi>end</hi> as the <hi>actuall</hi> fruit and effect of theſe <hi>meanes;</hi> and therefore if the Oathes objected doe oblige to <hi>deſtroy</hi> thoſe mean<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, and with them, the end by them already <hi>obtain'd;</hi> that is, if they oblige on the one ſide to <hi>ſubvert</hi> (and all <hi>diſobedience</hi> tends to <hi>ſubverſion</hi>) that Order and Government, publike Juſtice and Peace, which is at preſent in the Nation; and on the other ſide in its ſtead to <hi>introduce</hi> diſorder &amp; Anar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy, War and conſuſion which all diſobedience naturally tends to introduce; and all this upon pretonce to reob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain other meanes, if at leaſt truly meanes, though ſuch as according to the preſent poſture of the parties concern'd, probably are never, or if ever to be obtain'd, threatning to prove <hi>deſtructive</hi> to the end itſelf: in ſuch caſe (and it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be deny'd but ſuch is the preſent caſe if impartially ſtated) the Oathes objected apparently binde (if ſaid to binde) to that which in its owne nature, and neceſſari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly is <hi>privative</hi> of, and <hi>oppoſite</hi> to the <hi>publike good</hi> and <hi>wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>being</hi> of the Nation; and conſequently (the Exercita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor himſelfe being Judge) they are to be pronounced <hi>void,</hi> for to a ſinfull thing there can be no Obligation. So it remaines that the true <hi>intent</hi> of the Oathes in contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie, is finally lodg'd in the <hi>good</hi> of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth; neither have they any force to the <hi>deſtruction</hi> thereof, but muſt needs be <hi>void</hi> if ever ſo intended.</p>
               <p>By this times tis hop'd, wee have ſufficiency <hi>expedited</hi> our ſelves of the <hi>impeditive,</hi> which our Exercitator ſaies will not be granted, and demonſtrated the <hi>privative</hi> part of his diſtinction. Wee are now at leaſure to heare what he ſayes further. That of the <hi>Gibeonites</hi> is no way per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent to the preſent caſe, the inconvenience of that Oath being quite of another nature, bendes they were made <hi>ſervants,</hi> though there lives were ſpan'd, which they acknowledged to be at themercy of the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> who
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:114595:14"/>conſidering their ſervitude, were at no great loſſe by them. But that their Oath was unlawfull <hi>Vrſums</hi> flatly denies nay he poſitively affirmes,<note place="margin">Non ideo ſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur <hi>Gibeonitis</hi> iuramen <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tum quod ad illum obſtingantur &amp;c <hi>Vrſin.</hi> Cas. Tere. Pracept.</note> 
                  <hi>they were not bound to keepe it.</hi> But to paſſe over his impertinences, and come to his weakneſſe; here he tells us, and we had a glance at it before, <hi>hat all authority bangs no upon he back of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſorpation.</hi> NO? How comes he then to define it <hi>an intruſion into the Seat of authority,</hi> and a <hi>poſſeſſing</hi> and <hi>managing</hi> of the <hi>place</hi> and <hi>power</hi> thereof? So it ſeemes though they intrude into the Seat, yet they are out of the Seat; and though they poſſeſſ and manage the place and power, yet they neither poſſeſſ nor manage the place and power of Authority; which is a meer contradiction, and ſo muſt needs be falſe, becauſe no contradiction can be true. He is ſo ingenuous afterwards as to grant the Doctrine of <hi>obedience,</hi> ſo much better then his own of <hi>diſobedience,</hi> as that it will afford a <hi>little</hi> juſtice, but his own <hi>non.</hi> Well but he ſales wee were not taught this Doctrine of obedience, <hi>when the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men began to ſtand up, and waken the people to ſhake off expi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation and oppreſsion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Certainly when the Parliament began, wee were not taught by any, but ſuch as pleaded for the cauſe of that <hi>expiration</hi> and <hi>oppreſſion;</hi> whereof he ſpeakes, that the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons in Parliament were no Houſe, were uſurpers. And therefore tis plaine, that either this Exercitator from the beginning was one of the Common Enemies againſt whom wee Covenanted; or elſe contrary to the expreſſe Text of the Covenant in the fixt Article; hath made a <hi>defection</hi> to them, for the takes up their wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons and fights their Battels, however he would be thought a champion for he Covenant. Againe. I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but wonder at the ignorance of this ſilly Objection; for had the <hi>Expilation</hi> which he takes of beene ten-fold more then was, no man that either had <hi>Knowledge</hi> or <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience</hi> of what he taught, would have taught to have lifted up ſo much as a finger againſt the <hi>Expilator,</hi> had we not had the <hi>impreame power</hi> of the Nation in peaceable and plenary <hi>poſſeſſion,</hi> to <hi>call</hi> us forth by <hi>Authority</hi> and <hi>Commiſſion</hi> us into <hi>Order,</hi> and a cauſe <hi>unqueſtionably</hi> juſt to
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:114595:15"/>
                  <hi>juſtifie</hi> thoſe Commiſſions; nay, the War on the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments ſide being <hi>defenſive,</hi> not <hi>offenſive,</hi> the end could ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be the <hi>ſubverſion</hi> of that Order and Government, publike juſtice and peace which the Nation then actually enjoy'd, as our Exercitators end, though a pretender to be ſtudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous of Peace, really is, but indeed by a defence leſſe neceſſary then juſt, to prevent the <hi>ſubverſion</hi> of all theſe, <hi>apparently</hi> indeavour'd, by the <hi>actuall invaſion</hi> of Delin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quents of all ſorts and <hi>Sizes.</hi> The Doctrine of <hi>diſobedience</hi> then is <hi>peculiar</hi> to the Exercitator, and the reſt of the <hi>Parke,</hi> not as themſelves ſay of <hi>old Puritans,</hi> but what might more probably have beeene ſaid, new <hi>Phariſees,</hi> by the ſelfe-aſſuming ſtil, had they not told us themſelves, that they were a company of godly Miniſters. But <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainely for their new Doctrine of diſobedience, it hath no affinity, with that of the good <hi>old Puritans;</hi> but is as contrary to it, as light is to darkneſſe, as we ſhall ſhew hereafter in one of the moſt eminent.</p>
               <p>He tells us with great crye, and little wooll, that <hi>Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eouſneſſe exalts a Nation, and the Throne is eſtabliſht by righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eouſneſſe;</hi> what righteouſneſſe? a <hi>Titular</hi> righteouſneſſe without a <hi>Reall,</hi> nay with a <hi>Reall unrighteouſneſſe?</hi> The truth is a <hi>Reall</hi> righteouſneſſe, may ſometimes eſtabliſh the Throne without a <hi>Tituler,</hi> but certainely a <hi>Tituler</hi> without a <hi>Reall,</hi> or with a <hi>Reall</hi> unrighteouſneſſe never. We may ſay in ſome ſort, the coneatenations of provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence conſidered,<note place="margin">After noones preaching. Book of ſports. Innovations Maſſe it ſelfe.</note> that if <hi>Saul</hi> had not raigned in <hi>unrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, righteous David</hi> had never raigned. Had not <hi>unrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe</hi> beene propagated through the Nation, by the <hi>publike ſuppreſsion,</hi> and <hi>profanation</hi> of what was <hi>holy,</hi> and authorization of what was <hi>wicked</hi> and <hi>profane;</hi> and the almighty thereby provok't as 'twere <hi>to his face,</hi> poſſibly the Exercitators Pen might have beene idle, or found a better imployment.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder Vſurpation</hi> (he ſaies, meaning the preſent Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment in the <hi>American</hi> tongue) <hi>we can expect no ſettle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi> 'Tis granted, how can we, what need wee expect it? we have a ſettlement already, and <hi>Nthil appetit id quod habet.</hi> Deſire and expectation end, where fruition and
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:114595:15"/>enjoyment begin. Well, but however, hee ſaies, tis <hi>cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine</hi> to fall. <hi>Quod volumus facile credinues.</hi> Sure his cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty is but from an uncertaine and ſimplicite faith, that hath its eye blinded by that ignorance which is the mother of his devotiton to his owne cauſe. No, for he ſaies <hi>commotion is ſure in reaſonte follow.</hi> Sure enough from ſuch <hi>turbulent</hi> reaſon as hee gives us in his Exercitation; for therein he doth what he can to prove himſelfe a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, as true in his falſe prediction, as falſe in his untrue Doctrine: but ſure if the reaſons for obedience be as tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as truth would have them followed, commotion in rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon can never follow. 'Tis ſuch Doctrine as his owne without Religion, however pretending to reaſon, that raiſes the <hi>evill ſpirit</hi> of Commotion, which the <hi>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e and peaceable wiſed me that is from above,</hi> would ſoon <hi>lay</hi> and bind up forever. But we ſhall follow him no farther in theſe minute impertinences, but returne to the laſt prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple, which we here intend to inſiſt on.</p>
               <p>The caſe of impoſſibility is ſo evident in it ſelfe, and obvious to the meaneſt capacity, as no ſooner can it be ſaid, then aſſented to, that <hi>no Oath can oblige to doe that which cannot be done.</hi> To this our Exercitator page 44. Anſwers, <hi>All reaſonable men will grant ſo far as impoſsbility lyes, and ſo long as it continues, the Oath binds not; but this is not to our Authers puroſe, for to ceaſe from an Act, that is, from obedience, to the preſent Government, can never bee im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſsible.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The impoſſibility which the Exercitator denyes, and his oppoſite affirmes, muſt concerne either the <hi>Act</hi> to be perform'd, or the <hi>lawfulneſſe</hi> of the performance. If both theſe be prov'd againſt him, the Authors argument ſtands good and the Exercitators exception againſt it falls to the ground. Now tis certaine as the preſent caſe ſtands, tis both <hi>impoſſible</hi> to obey the former Powers, and <hi>unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full</hi> to diſobey the preſent. The former cannot with the leaſt ſhadow of reaſon be deny'd, and indeed the Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citator ſeemes to grant it, whilſt he puts the whole ſtreſſe of his anſwer upon a bare <hi>ceſſation,</hi> or <hi>non-acting</hi> in obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to the preſent Government. For tis plainely as
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:114595:16"/>impoſſible to give <hi>actuall</hi> obedience to any power there, where there is no power <hi>actually</hi> to command, as tis for <hi>Caius</hi> being in the evening at <hi>London,</hi> to meet <hi>Titius</hi> thenext morning at <hi>Venice;</hi> or it you will, as impoſſible (to come nearer to the preſent caſe) as 'tis for <hi>caius</hi> being in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> to yeeld ſubjection there to the ſoveraigne power of <hi>Titius</hi> being in <hi>Venice;</hi> when indeed others are <hi>actually</hi> and <hi>plenarily</hi> poſſeſt of the ſoveraigne power in <hi>England;</hi> and <hi>Titius</hi> hath <hi>actually</hi> no part in the ſoveraigne power there.<note place="margin">The Exercita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaies as much, p 9.</note> The reaſon is evident in the Axiome, <hi>Relata mutuò ſe ponunt ac tellunt,</hi> Relatives (and ſuch are ſove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rainty and ſubjection) ſtand and fall together. Where there is no power to command, it muſt needs bee impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible to obey, becauſe obedience properly preſuppoſes a power commanding, and acommandment to be obey'd. The latter is as truely unlawfull, as the former appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently impoſſible. For tis a ſin againſt <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.7. Not <hi>to render honour, to whom honour is due;</hi> but honour is due to thoſe that <hi>receive tribute, for they are Gods Miniſters, at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending continually upon this very thing, v.</hi> 6. to thoſe that are <hi>Miniſters under God for our good,</hi> and for <hi>vengeance and wrath to evil doers,</hi> and ſo both actually <hi>beare the Sword,</hi> and beare it <hi>not in vaine v.</hi> 4. to thoſe that being actually <hi>Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers,</hi> are <hi>a terrour to evill workes, and a praiſe to them that doe well, v.</hi> 3. In a word, to thoſe that are <hi>Ordained of God,</hi> and they are <hi>the Powers that are; For there is no power but of God, and the power that are, are ordained of God, v.</hi> 1. to thoſe honour is due. Can any thing be ſpoken more plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for the duty of rendering honour to preſent powers? Let's ſee now our Exercitators Doctrine, how agreeable it is to this of the Apoſtle. Honour, he ſaies, is not due to thoſe that are Gods Miniſters continually attending, not to thoſe that receive tribute, not to thoſe that are Gods Miniſters for vengeance and wrath to evill doers; not to thoſe that beare the Sword, and beare it not in vaine; not to thoſe that are Miniſters under God for our good, not to thoſe that being actually Rulers, are a terrour to evill workes, and a praiſe to ſuch as doe well; in a word,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:114595:16"/>not to the powers that are. To thoſe honour is not due No? to whom then? to thoſe, ſaies our Exercitator, that are not Gods Miniſters continually attending, receive not Tribute, are not Gods Miniſters for wrath, beare not the Sword, are not Gods Miniſters for good; not Rulers, not a terrour to the evill, not a praiſe to the good; finally to thoſe that <hi>ARE NOT,</hi> to thoſe ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour is due. To thoſe? why to thoſe? why? becauſe according to our Exercitators Doctrine, when the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſaies the powers <hi>that are,</hi> are ordained of God, he meanes the powers that <hi>are not;</hi> and when he ſaies, there is NO power but of God, his meaning is, there are <hi>ſome</hi> powers (ſupream powers) that are not of God: laſtly, when he ſaies, let EVERY ſoul be ſubject, his mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning is, let <hi>ſome</hi> ſoules <hi>not be ſubject.</hi> Can any thing be ſpoken more ridiculouſly abſur'd in it ſelf, more contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictorie to the word of God by his Apoſtle, to the minde of God in his word, or indeed to reaſon and common ſence? But hold a little, why muſt thoſe that are not, be obey'd, and thoſe that are, diſobey'd? Why? be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>William</hi> the Conquerour had a lawfull calling from the people, but the Commons in Parliament have none. And yet the truth is, it may with no leſſe evidence then truth, and as much as both of is poſſible, be aſſerted, that there is not that ſupream power this day under the Sun, which hath ſo expreſſe and full a calling from the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; the people in ſo full a latitude, as the Commons of <hi>England</hi> in Parliament; unleſſe it be among the <hi>Maca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riens,</hi> not long ſince brought to light by the diſcoveries of <hi>Raphael, H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>deaeus.</hi> But to return thither whence we digreſt, tis evident by every ſtroke and lineament of the powers, which the Apoſtledeſcribes and limnes out to be obey'd, that he meanes powers <hi>actually</hi> impowred, and not a power <hi>actually</hi> diſ-empowred, and in that reſpect, a <hi>meere Ens rationis.</hi> And therefore if honour (which compar'd with the fifth Commandment, takes in the full latitude of obedience) muſt in duty be given to thoſe, to whom the Apoſtle ſaies it is due, and it be due, by the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:114595:17"/>Doctrine, to the powers that ARE and ACT; it followes, tis impoſſible to ceaſe from an Act; that is, from obedience to the preſent Covernment, becauſe, <hi>Id tantum poſſumus quod jure poſſumus,</hi> whatſoever is unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, is alſo in that reſpect impoſſible, and therefore we may not diſobey the preſent Government, becauſe the word commands to obey them; neither can any Oath diſoblige from this duty of obedience, or oblige to the ſin of diſobedience, for <hi>Rei illicitae nu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>a obligatio.</hi> To a ſinfull thing (as our Exercitator ſpeakes) there can be no Obligation. So it remaines, that our Authors ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument was full, and the Exercitators exception is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to the purpoſe.</p>
               <p>There is yet one Objection behinde, which clear'd, cleares up this part of the controverſie. For tis urg'd, that <hi>To obey Powers poſſeſt by wrong, is to juſtifie the Poſſeſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>urs wrong, and wrong the right of the diſpoſſeſt; and therefore ſuch obedience can be no duty but a ſin.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The anſwer is cleare. Obedience doth indeed juſtifie, that to which it is properly and <hi>formally</hi> given. But the Obedience aſſerted is not ſo to be given, either to the <hi>Act</hi> of Uſurpation in entring, or the perſon of the Uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, <hi>as entring</hi> by ſuch an <hi>Act</hi> into the ſupreame Power. But the truth is, the obedience maintained, is properly and <hi>formally</hi> to be given: Firſt, to the <hi>Ordinance</hi> of God in the hand of the perſon actually entred. Neither can it, without manifeſt contradiction to the word of truth, be deny'd, that the Sword or ſupreame power, which is actually a terrour to evill doers, and a praiſe to them that doe well, and therefore is not borne in vaine, is truly the Ordinance of God. And ſecondly obedience (as tis aſſerted) is properly and <hi>formally</hi> to be given to the perſon <hi>actually</hi> entred; not as entring by Uſurpati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but as that perſon to whom the moſt High thinkes meete to give the Kingdome of men, who by that ſove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne abſolute and univerſall right which he claimes as ſole Lord and maker of All; givesit both from, and to whomſoever he thinkes meete; and who many times for
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:114595:17"/>cauſes beſt knowne to himſelfe, thinks meet, both to give it from thoſe who among men have an acknowledg'd right; and to thoſe who have no other right among men, but what himſelfe as the moſt High, that rules in the Kingdome of men, by vertue of his owne ſupreame and abſolute right, is pleaſed from his owne <hi>actuall giſt</hi> and donation to confer upon them. And this alſo is a truth ſo manifeſt from the word of truth, in that 27. Chapter of <hi>Jeremy;</hi> as nothing can be ſpoken with a more tranſcendent majeſty, both of evidence and autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity. For we all know concerning the Kingdome of <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dabh,</hi> that the unqueſtionable right, as to man was ſolely in the houſe of <hi>David:</hi> neither can we be ignorant, that therefore as to man, <hi>Nebuehadnezzar</hi> could have no right in the leaſt to that Kingdome. Yet the moſt High God having firſt premiſed verſe. 5. his abſolute ſoverainty, and ſoverain right, (by vertue of his bringing forth all things, into their reſpective beings, by the exerted arme of his Almighty power) to the diſpenſation of all things ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his pleaſure, acquaints us with the pleaſure of his diſpenſation, concerning the Kingdome of <hi>Judah,</hi> and with it all other Lands that ſunke under the weight and force of the victorious Sword of the Babylonian King, in theſe words verſ. 6. <hi>And now have</hi> I GIVEN <hi>all theſe Lands into the hands of</hi> Nebuchadnezzar <hi>the King of Babylon my ſervant &amp;c.</hi> And in the proceſſe, a univerſall obedience is peremtorily commanded, and diſobedience threatned with ſevereſt chaſtiſements. From all which it is evident, that God himſelfe expreſly, both ownes the giving of power to thoſe who have no Title in point of Right; and both commands obedience, and for bids diſobedience to thoſe who (though God hath alwaies a deſigne above them) poſſeſſe themſelves of power by force and Uſurpation. And to the truth of this parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular, and the deduction of this truth from the grounds before us, we have the teſtimony of Mr. <hi>Calvin,</hi> with that fulneſſe as more cannot be ſaid. Speaking of Nebuchad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nezzar, heſaies:</p>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:114595:18"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Now What manner of King</hi> Nebuchadnezzer <hi>was, he that ſeekt</hi> Jeruſalem,<note place="margin">Jam qualis ren faerit <hi>Nebu chadnezar,</hi> is qui <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> expugnavit, ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis ſcitur, nempe ſtrenuns alio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum invaſor ac populator. <hi>Cal. Inſt. lib. 4. Cap. 20. § 26.</hi> Videmus quantâ obedientia Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minus tetrum il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum ferocem<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> tyrannum coli woluit, non alia ratione niſi quia regnum obtaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat. <hi>Ibid. § 27</hi> Eruſtra objiciar quis mandatum illud fuiſſe Iſraelitis peeuliare, Obſervandum enim eſt quâ ratione ipſum Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minus ſtabiliat; Deiuli, inquit, <hi>Nebuchadnezari</hi> regnum quare ſervite ills. &amp; vivite. Cui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuno; erge delatum fuiſſe regnum conſtalit, ei ſerviendum eſſe ne dubitemas. At<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſemnlac in regium faſtigium quempiam evehit Dominus, teſtatam nobis facis ſuam voluntatem, quod reg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nare illum velit.</note> 
                  <hi>is ſufficiently known; to wit,</hi> a mighty Uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, <hi>and oen that made ſpeile of others.</hi> And after wards ſpeaking to Jerem. 27. <hi>We ſee (ſaies he) with what great obedience the Lord would have that cruell and fierce Tyrant to be honoured, for</hi> no <hi>other reaſon, but becauſe he was in</hi> poſſeſſion <hi>of the Kingdome.</hi> But that which follows, exceeds what hath been ſaid, and is indeed as much as in the preſent caſe can be ſaid. <hi>In voine may any one Object,</hi> that <hi>command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment [of obedience] was</hi> peculiar to the Iſraelites. <hi>For the reaſon muſt be conſider'd upon which the Lord grounds it;</hi> I have given (ſaies he) <hi>the Kingdome to</hi> Nebuchadnezzer. <hi>Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſerve ye him, and live. To whomſoever therefore the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preame Power ſhall appeare to be given; let us never doubt but we muſt obey him. Seeing as ſoon as the Lord raiſes any perſon to a ſtate of ſoverainty, he gives us to know tis his expreſſe</hi> will <hi>that ſuch a one have the Government.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Upon he whole, the concluſion will bee evident in its owne light, and fairely untye the knot of the preſent Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection. For, to give obedience to the Ordinance of God, can never juſtifie the diſorder of man; neither can a ſubmiſſion to the ſupreame right of God, be in any ſort an injury to the ſubordinate right of man. Which gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted (as it cannot be deny'd) the obedience aſſerted can never be a <hi>Sin,</hi> but continues ſtilll a <hi>Duty,</hi> againſt which no Oath hath power to oblige. And thus far ſhall ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice to have aſſerted this Truth, that <hi>The Oathes objected oblige not againſt Obedience to preſent Powers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But before we proceed to the third Aſſertion, although (as we ſaid in the beginning) our intention is not to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into a <hi>Logomachie,</hi> or word-wrangle with the Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citator, wherein to give him his due, it muſt be confeſt he hath deſerv'd very well of the whole frye of School-boyes,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:114595:18"/>and given them much light into their true <hi>Syntaxis</hi> (as he ſpeakes page 48.) in his large and exquiſite Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments upon the Pronouns and Conjunctions Copulative, and diſiunctive; <hi>Him</hi> and <hi>Them,</hi> and <hi>Her,</hi> and <hi>Their,</hi> and <hi>His,</hi> and <hi>Her,</hi> and <hi>Or,</hi> and <hi>And</hi> &amp;c. Shewing himſelfe a moſt profound Grammaticaſter: Yet ſeeing his impotence cannot thinke it ſelfe conſpicuous enough in it ſelfe, without being injurious to others; we cannot but take notice and give the Reader a ſhort account of his injuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, though impotent inſinuation repeated (according to his uſuall veine of Tautologies) thrice over (Page 18.43, 52.) againſt the Author of <hi>The lawſulneſſe of obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>It is to be admired</hi> (he ſaies) <hi>That the Author ſhould be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin with a generall Deliberative</hi> [It were good to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered &amp;c.] <hi>And yet end with onely a particular inſtance in one of the Oathes to be conſidered.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Admiration (tis uſually ſaid) is the childe of Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance; and tis true (if ever) here of our learned Exercita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors double, if not treble ignorance, in reſpect both of the preſent ground of his admiration, and his miſtake a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the meaning, both of the Author and Oath.</p>
               <p>For firſt, what neceſſity is, there I pray, that he that propounds matter worthy of generall conſideration to others, muſt therefore himſelfe enter into a particular enumeration of particulars? As if hee that ſhould ſay, it were good to conſider, whether the ſo much applauded Exercitation bee not a piece that deſerves better to bee exploded, and inſtance onely in page 88. where the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercitator beſides his falfifying the Hiſtory alleg'd, and with it the truth it ſelfe, ſhewes himſelfe after all his diſcourſe about true <hi>Syntaxis,</hi> unable to conſtrue his own Latin; ſhould yet bee bound to follow him in a particular inveſtigation of his perplext impertinencies, from his firſt entrance into his <hi>Amercian</hi> deſerts, Page 5. to Page 88. before mentioned, which ſhuts up his idle Exercitation. Obut he ſaies, <hi>The Author ſeemes to faſten on that inſtance, becauſe he thoughthimſelfe beſt able to looſen
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:114595:19"/>its Obligation.</hi> A piece of diſcretion i'le aſſure you, of which if the Exercitator had beene guilty, he had never undertaken to looſen ſoules from ſubjection to the powers that are, by endeavouring to faſten on them the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of diſobedience, though he were faine to ſneake into <hi>America</hi> to fetch it. But <hi>he leaves the judgement of the Authors performance</hi> to the Reader; and ſo ſhall wee of his.</p>
               <p>But firſt hee falls into another fit of Admiration. What's the matter! He admires, <hi>Seeing the Author ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts Oathes ſacred Bonds and reverend Obligements; how he feared not to uſe ſuch enforcement, to the cleare letter of ſo tender and ſacred a thing. Bona verba!</hi> If (before we diſmiſſe the Exercitator) we finde not himſelfe really guilty of an <hi>enforcement</hi> to learned <hi>Paraeus,</hi> not much better (for the nature of enforcement is the ſame, however the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject differ) then that which is here but pretended, and that too without the leaſt ground given by our Author, but meerely taken from his owne ignorance, and ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mered out into the deformed piece of perjury in the charge, upon the black forge of his owne miſtake; we ſhall allow him to fall into a third fit of Admiration. In the meane time whilſt he endeavours wrongfully to faſten on our Author, an interpretation begotten (like <hi>Ixion's</hi> Centaures) on the Cloud of his owne miſ-ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion, what doth be but create a fault, that he may not want an accuſation, though he bring himſelfe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the guilt of <hi>bearing falſe witneſſe</hi> againſt his Neighbour by it, which (as he ſpeakes) borders upon <hi>Perjury;</hi> and ſurely is not very agreeable to that Hyperbolcall Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter of the Exercitator, held forth in the glorious buſh of the Epiſtle to the Reader.</p>
               <p>Wherefore of ſhow the true intent of our Author, and with all the untrue, charge of this Accuſer; Our Author (as we can ſpeake from ſome that have reaſon to know) never intended the preſent Powers, as the Succeſſours in the Oath, at the Exercitator ingorantly, or maliciouſly, or both (let him take his choice) miſtakes him; his
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:114595:19"/>intention in truth (and his diſcourſe teſtifies as much) was onely to inforce a <hi>Dilemma,</hi> upon thoſe that argue for the Obligation of the Oath. For he reaſons, that if Heires and Succeſſors muſt, (as the Exercitator and all that are of his judgement, ſay they muſt,) be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood of the ſame perſons, the Obligation of the Oath muſt needs ceaſE upon ſuch a juncture of affaires, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in neither the Succeſſors are Heires, nor the Heires Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors. And to take off the Objection of a Succeſſion in <hi>Right,</hi> though not in <hi>Fact;</hi> He ſhew'd that that word uſually is, and therefore truly muſt (as indeed it muſt) be underſtood in the Oath of <hi>actual</hi> Succeſſours; un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe a Nation may bee Governed by, and give obedience to a meere <hi>Ens rationis;</hi> for a Succeſſor in right onely, though never ſo truely in right, as ſuch, is ſuch or no better. Behold the ſtrength of the perjurious ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſation, or more truly the weakneſſe of the injurious ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſer, after all thoſe ſolmne aggravations, in which hee hath dreſt up his accuſation, and his grave advice to the Author upon it; whereas indeed had himſelfe beene ſo well adviſed, as he ſhould have been, he never had laid ſo heavy a charge upon ſo light, or in truth, no ground, on a perſon of whom he confeſſes to have receav'd ſo <hi>faire a Character</hi> from the worthy Author of the <hi>religious De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>murrer.</hi> And now after his threefold attempt on the word <hi>Succeſſors,</hi> to wound the reputation of our Author, becauſe here (at leaſt) hee thought he had met with a <hi>Flaw,</hi> what is all he hath gained, ſave onely a fuller con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation, both of our Authors integrity, and the truth aſſerted by him, and a further diſcovery both of the weakneſſe of his cauſe, and the greatneſſe of his little good-will towards our Author?</p>
               <q>— Fragili quaerens illidere dentem, Offendit ſolido.</q>
               <p>But ſeeing he talkes of an Enforcement to the cleare letter of the Oath (though indeed the true ſence of an
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:114595:20"/>Oath, more then of the Scripture it ſelfe, is not alwaies to be finally determined by the Letter) what will he ſay, if it be prov'd againſt himſelfe, that he is truly guilty of the enforcement, untruly charg'd by him on our Author? may he not then juſtly bee ſtruck into a worſe fit then any of the former, not of Admiration, but aſtoniſhment? Yet peradventure this is not a thing altogether impoſſible nay poſſibly it may be done in very few words. Wherefore though we aſſert nothing Magiſterially, yet to meet with our Exercitator in the ſame path which himſelfe hath chalk tout, we ſhall commend the ſequele to the ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and impartiall confideration and judgement of the Reader.</p>
               <p>Out of his owne mouth ſhall wee judge our Exercita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor. For page. 48. He tells us, that by Succeſſion in the Oath, muſt be intended heires <hi>in Succeſſion.</hi> It followes then, that by his owne confeſſion, the Oath obliges not to Heires <hi>out of Succeſſion.</hi> And indeed herein he ſpeakes reaſon, though afterwards he is ſo unhappy, as to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradict both reaſon and himſelfe, when hee lights upon it; for he would have thoſe termed Succeſſors which doe not actually ſucceed, which may be with as much pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priety of ſpeech (for Oathes ſure doe not uſe to ſpeake in <hi>Tropes</hi>) as <hi>Mons</hi> may be ſaid <hi>à movendo.</hi> He pretends that our Authors interpretation borders upon perjury; but I am ſure his owne both borders upon it, and falls into the very boſome of non-ſence. No he ſaies, for there is a ſucceſſion in Right, as well as in Fact. What then? A ſucceſſion in Right, and not in Fact, is not bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then no ſucceſſion to the Nation. Doth the Oath binde to <hi>actual Obedience</hi> to a perſon that is not an <hi>actuall Succeſſor?</hi> An evident impoſsibility to give actuall obedience to a perſon that doth not actually ſuicceed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Incidit in Scillam</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>But he hath yet another ſtring to his Bow. For hee ſaies the Oath of Supremacy binds to a <hi>lawfull</hi> Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor.
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:114595:20"/>Much to the purpoſe. How can he be a lawfull Succeſſor that (as K.) doth not ſucceed at all? <hi>Non entis nul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo ſunt accidentia.</hi> But the truth is, it had been good this Author had underſtood the true ſtate of the Oath of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacy, before he had adventured upon it. To doe that hee ſhould have conſulted with 5. <hi>Eliz.</hi> and that would have conducted him to an Injunction, in the premonition to which Injunction, hee would have found that this Oath was to bee interpreted and taken In this ſence <hi>viz. To exnelude all forraigne Iuriſdiction.</hi> And ſo he might have ſpar'd his Logick and Rhetoricke both, concerning this Oath, which as is wholly unconcerned in the preſent caſe; for here is no queſtion about <hi>Forraigne juiſdiction.</hi> But to omit this and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed; what if by the lawes of the Land, a Succeſſor, <hi>in Fact,</hi> be a <hi>lawfull</hi> Succeſſor, at leaſt untill he be <hi>lawfully rmov'd,</hi> hath hee any whit advantaged himſelfe by the word <hi>Lawfull?</hi> Yet that ſo it is, ſeemes to be very cleare in the caſe of <hi>H.</hi> 7. If we will receive the verdict of the Sages of the Law, the company of Judges aſſembled in the Exchequer Chamber upon it, even when his Perſon was actually under an attaindour of Treaſon, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Parliament confer'd that right which the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercitator contradicting himſelfe (as wee ſhall ſhew elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where) would pretend; Heart their words as they are gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven us by the Lord <hi>Verulam; It was</hi> (ſaies he) <hi>with</hi> una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimous conſent <hi>reſolved, That the Crowne takes away all</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects <hi>and ſtops in blood; from the time the</hi> King <hi>did</hi> aſſume <hi>the Crowne, the Fountaine was cleared, and all attaindours and corruptions of blood diſcharged.</hi> What can be more plaine?<note place="margin">Bacon <hi>H. 7.</hi> page 13.</note> From the time he aſſum'd the Crowne, that is, after his <hi>actuall poſſeſſion</hi> of ſoverainty and <hi>Succeſſion</hi> to the former King, although his Title had before beene condemned by Parliament in <hi>H.</hi> 6. and the Succeſſion <hi>in right,</hi> were then in the Lady <hi>Elizibeth,</hi> yet the Succeſſour <hi>in fact</hi> is unanimouſy acknowledged a <hi>lawfull</hi> Succeſſor in the ſoverainty. Againe, It was (ſaies our Author) agreed and reſolv'd by the ſame Judges, and their Reſolutions
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:114595:21"/>were accordingly follow'd by the Parliament then fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting; <hi>That the Knights and Burgeſſes ſhould forbeare to come into the Houſe, till a Law were paſt for the reverſall of thoſe attainders,</hi> under which he had ſaid before divers of them were, for a acting againſt, <hi>R.</hi> 3. whom all the world ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledges to have been an Uſurper. Where, beſide the confutation of the Exercitators Doctrine, page 7. That, the Houſe muſt bee free for all to come to, that their Acts may be free and authoritative; It is worth the Readers moſt ſerious obſervation, that by the opinion of the Judges generally aſſembled, an attainder may be brought in for Treaſon againſt an <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurper,</hi> and ſtands good in Law,<note place="margin">
                     <p>
                        <hi>Nota,</hi> Diciair &amp; non negaiur quod proditione facta tempore <hi>H.</hi> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>qui fuit uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per del Crowne le partie ſera ar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>raigne de ceau tempore <hi>E. 4.</hi> vel bujus modi, per compaſſant le more regis po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et eſſe pune tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pere alterius, Regi: Comment que l'un ſuet <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurp.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Brook, Grand Abrigement Tit. Treaſon.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </note> untill by courſe of Law it be reverſt, though the Uſurper himſelf were remov'd. Which proves clearely, that Treaſon is truly Treaſon by the Law of the Land, though committed againſt an Uſurper. And to this <hi>Brooke,</hi> gives a full and cleare teſtimony; for <hi>Note,</hi> ſaies he, <hi>It is affirmed beyond contradiction, that for treaſon committed in the time of</hi> H. 6. <hi>who was an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurper of the Crowne, the partie ſhall be arraigned thereof in the time of</hi> Edw. 4. <hi>Or ſuch a perſon may be puniſht in the time of an other King, for compaſſing the death of a King that was an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurper.</hi> By all which it is cleare, that a Succeſſor <hi>in Fact,</hi> by the Law of the Land, is a <hi>lawfull</hi> Succeſſor, untill lawfully re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mov'd. And that paſſage concerning <hi>H.</hi> 6. is very re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable. For when <hi>Richard Duke</hi> of <hi>Yorke,</hi> had Seated himſelfe in the Chaire of State in the Lords houſe in Parliament, and there laid claime to the Crowne, and made good his claime and Title to the Parliament, tis ſaid, <hi>VVhen the Lords and Commons there aſſembled, had with mature deliberation and good advice,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Marting Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the Kings and Queens of <hi>Engl. pag. 258.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>ſoundly debated on this im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portant buſineſſe, it was by them all enacted, that King</hi> H. <hi>ſhould ſo long as he lived, retaine the name and honour of a King</hi> &amp;c. So great reſpect had our Anceſtours to Succeſſors in Fact, even where the Succeſſor in Right, and of eminent worth and abilities was preſent, and claiming, and had judgement alſo given on his ſide. And upon the ground in Law before mentioned, was the Statute of 11.
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:114595:21"/>
                  <hi>H.</hi> 7. Enacted, which frees from the guilt of Treaſon, for adhering to Succeſſors in Fact. But the Exercitation eſpies yet another advantage in the Oath, by which hee makes account eaſily to elude all this; for he ſaies the ſucceſsion is to <hi>a Crown and Dignity,</hi> but <hi>that is aboliſh;</hi> and therefore the Succeſſors which he pretends our Author pleads for, can never be thoſe intended in the Oath. Is it indeed abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſht? How then can the Succeſſor which he pleads for, bee the Succeſſor in the Oath, more then they? nay how can he indeed be either Succeſſor or Heire? Hee that is either Heire or Succeſſor to that which is a aboliſh, is ſuch to that which is not; hee that is ſuch to that which is not, is ſuch to that which is indeed nothing; much good do it him, both with his Heire and Succeſſor-ſhip; the man hath fairely confuted himſelfe. But then againe, doth he know what the Crowne and Dignity he talkes on, is? Doth its eſſence conſiſt in a <hi>Name</hi> or <hi>Thing?</hi> If in a Name, There is no body deſires much to take it from him, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided he be contented with that onely. If it conſiſt in a Thing, then the name is onely chang'd, the thing ſtill re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines, and ſo they of whom our Author (as he would pretend) ſpeakes, may be the Succeſſors in the Oath, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding what he Objects to the contrary, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the aboliſhing of the Crowne and Dignity. Yet againe he ſales, the Oath intends by Heires and Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors the <hi>Jame Perſons,</hi> which he goes about to prove, too ridiculouſly to neede an anſwer, and adds, <hi>admit them divers, and the Oath will import a contradiction.</hi> For he ſaies, had the perſons beene divers, it muſt have beene <hi>Heires</hi> [or] not [and] <hi>Succeſſors.</hi> Right. For you know in a Leaſe, we muſt not ſay Executors, Adminiſtrators [and] Aſsignes, but [or] Aſsignes, unleſſe Aſsignes meane the ſame perſons, with Executors and Adminiſtrators, elſe it will imply a contradiction. Where's his true <hi>Syn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taxis</hi> now? will not every Scrivener tell him that this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves the <hi>Ferula?</hi> Againe, admit them divers, and the Oath will import a contradiction. A very weake excepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:114595:22"/>but a ſtrong contradiction to the truth, and therein a reall inforcement to the cleare Letter of the Oath; his over-haſty zeale making him truely fall into that very crime, which he had before wrongfully charg'd on our Author. For why I pray, may we not ſwear to performe the duty of the Oath, to divers ſorts of perſons, at divers times obtaining, and without a contradiction; ſeeing both cannot obtain at once, if the words beare adifferent ſignification? And that their ſignification is indeed differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, The Exercitator himſelf cannot deny, whilſt he grants the word [Succeſſours] even in the preſent Oath to bee a <hi>Terme in Law,</hi> Page 50. For every <hi>Puiſne</hi> will tell him that hath but read the firſt Chapter in <hi>Littleton,</hi> that words that make a <hi>different eſtate</hi> in Law, muſt in Law have a <hi>different ſignification.</hi> Beſides reaſon it ſelfe will dictate, that they were at firſt intended <hi>different.</hi> For the Oath being made by the Kingdome in Parliament, was intended to make proviſion for the Kingdome, as well as the King; (and not for the King, without the Kingdome, as the Exercitator ſondly imagines) in caſe the line obtaining ſhould faile, or upon other emergen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies whatever that might inſue. To conclude this parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular; our Author to ſhew the ordinary acception of the word Succeſſor, bids aske the queſtion, who was Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſour to <hi>W.</hi> Conqueror. The Exercitator takes him up very Magiſterially and ſaies, <hi>tis fallaciouſly propounded.</hi> Rightly, he ſaies, 'twill be this, <hi>Who is to bee his Majeſties Succeſſour?</hi> But ſurely hee hath not more fallaciouſly, then fooliſhly propounded a queſtion, which Fryer <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons</hi> head would hardly have beene able to anſwer him. For if it muſt be underſtood, as he tells us he intends it, <hi>Of the ſuture time, and a thing to be done in it;</hi> He that ſhall give a true anſwer to the queſtion ſo propounded, and ſo underſtood, muſt either anſwer by <hi>inſpiration,</hi> or confeſſe that our learned Exercitator hath clearely put him to a <hi>non-plns.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Before we conclude this Chapter, we cannot but taſte
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:114595:22"/>of one more diſh of Objections ſerv'd in (as indeed it is ſomewhat a homely o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e) our of a Homily. For hee tells us the Homily is fully and flatly againſt Subjects <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moving or diſpoſing</hi> (ſure it ſhould bee depoſing) their Princes upon any pretence whatſoever. This Homily he ſaies is part of the Doctrine of the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land;</hi> and this Doctrine of the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> hee ſaies, wee are bound by Proteſtation to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine; and this ſticks very much with him, for he knowes not how the contrary can ſtand with the Proteſtation. Well, for this once I ſhall undertake with his owne, and the helpe of the Fuller Anſwer to be his <hi>Oedipus.</hi> I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer therefore, If he pleaſe to call it to minde, he may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member he told us, that in his <hi>America</hi> the Houſe of Commons, were coordinate with the <hi>American</hi> Prince; now if he doe not underſtand his owne Termes, the Ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler Anſwer will tell him, that where there is a <hi>Coordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> there is no <hi>Subordination,</hi> but <hi>Subjects</hi> are <hi>Subordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate;</hi> therefore he addes, that all the Members <hi>Collectine</hi> in their Houſe, are not Subjects. Againe, our Exercita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor makes his coordinate Commons, the <hi>Fundament Us</hi> of his <hi>American</hi> Government. And in this caſe the Fuller Anſwer will tell him againe, <hi>Fundamentalls</hi> admit not of <hi>higher</hi> and <hi>lower;</hi> all foundations are <hi>principall</hi> alike, there can be therefore no ſubjection. So it is not much mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall, whether his Homily be part of the Doctrine of the Church of <hi>England</hi> or no, for the practiſe in <hi>America,</hi> is not contrary to the Doctrine in <hi>England.</hi> But certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſome that have reaſon to know, ſay that thoſe Homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies are no part of the Doctrine of the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land:</hi> and that the Articles give them onely this Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, that they containe wholſome Doctrine, and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to their times. But enough, if not too much of this we haſten to our third Aſſertion.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:114595:23"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IIII.</hi> That obedience is due to Powers in poſſeſſion, though unlawfully entred.</head>
               <p>IN anſwering the Arguments, from the Oathes object<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the former Chapter, againſt obedience to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Powers, when ſuppoſ'd to bee unlawfully entred; there was frequent cauſe to demonſtrate the Duty of ſuch obedience, which properly ſhould have beene the worke of the preſent Aſſertion, wherefore having as to the point in hand already ſpoken ſo much, ſo much the leſſe will need now to be added.</p>
               <p>The Exercitator page 64. acknowledges, <hi>The lawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of obeying</hi> &amp;c. hath of all others, ſpoken moſt for the obedience to be maintained; and upon that account tels us, he intends to ſpeake moſt againſt what was by him ſpoken. We ſhall herein follow the path which he hath thus trod out to us, and if we doe but make good our Authors part againſt his Antagoniſt, wee ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feate his maine Battell by his owne confeſſion.</p>
               <p>The firſt taske he undertakes, is, to prove that the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle in the place urg'd by our Author, (<hi>Rom.</hi> 13.) can onely bee underſtood of a <hi>lawfull</hi> Magiſtracy, and to make that good, compares it (as he had done before, in laying his foundation page 1.) with <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 8.4. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if here we finde his foundation <hi>Sandy,</hi> his whole edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice will ſufficiently appeare to be <hi>ruinous</hi> To proceed then, from the compariſon of thoſe two Scriptures he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes page 66. That the former ſpeakes of a <hi>legall,</hi> the latter of an <hi>illegal</hi> Magiſtracie, elſe they would be <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradictory.</hi> Wherein I am ſure he is contradictory to his owne Doctrine, as his owne Doctrine is contradictory
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:114595:23"/>to the truth, and conſequently needs no other Judge, but his owne mouth to condeme it. For firſt, he is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parently contradictory to himſelfs, in that at the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, he would have Uſurpers to be <hi>but private perſons,</hi> Page 9. and <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. muſt be underſtood (how uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſally ſoever ſpoken) of a <hi>lagal</hi> Magiſtracy <hi>onely;</hi> yet in concluſion, he findes a diſtinction betweene a <hi>legall</hi> and <hi>illegall</hi> Magiſtracy. But why? you will ſay there may be a faire anſwer to all this; the contradiction is onely in termes, not in things, in appeareance, not truth; by ille<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall Magiſtracy, hee meanes no other then Uſurpers. Do's he meane Uſurpers? then clearely hee confutes, as well as contradicts his owne Doctrine. For if he doe (as indeed he does) here intend <hi>Ieroboam</hi> and his Succeſſors, whom as here, ſo before in the entrance of his diſcourſe, he ſtrongly proves to be Uſurpers, both by this very Scripture, and the judgement of divers lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Divines upon the place; then certainly the confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed pile of the whole diſcourſe, like Babilon is fallen; and we need no other proſpect to behold its ruine, then the light and advantage which the preſent Scripture will afford us. For firſt, whereas hee would make Uſurpers <hi>no more but private perſons,</hi> who ſees not that as himſelfe here termes them Magiſtrates, though as to their Title and entrance into the Magiſtracy, they were <hi>illegall</hi> and Uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers: So this very Scripture which he brings to prove them Uſurpers; and their Hiſtory in Scripture records them by the Name, Title, State, and Dignity, of the Kings and Princes of Iſrael? And ſecondly, whereas he would prove that obedience is not due to Uſurpers, becauſe as our Exercitator would pretend they are <hi>no Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates;</hi> who knowes not that thoſe Uſurping Princes were the Magiſtrates of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and <hi>Obadiah, Eliah,</hi> and divers other Prophets and Servanas of God gave obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to them according yes to their Magiſtrates? Laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, what doth he but <hi>Nodum in ſcirpo quaerere,</hi> in ſetting the Scriptures, mentioned at ſuch a diſtance? Seeing
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:114595:24"/>
                  <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 8.4. ſpeakes <hi>expreſly</hi> of Powers, <hi>in fieri</hi> in their <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance,</hi> concerning their <hi>making</hi> or <hi>ſetting</hi> up. But <hi>Rom.</hi> 13 ſpeakes of Powers <hi>in facto eſſe,</hi> in <hi>poſſeſſion</hi> and <hi>acting,</hi> as <hi>Miniſters</hi> for the good of mankinde, from verſe 1. to verſe 7. And ſo we may helpe his memory, for by his frequent contradictions he ſeemes to need it, to untye this knot from his owne words, Page 2. Where he tells us concerning <hi>Jeroboam</hi> and his Succeſſors, That the <hi>Event</hi> and effect, that is (or I know not what it is) their <hi>actuall poſſeſſion</hi> of Power, and <hi>acting</hi> in a way of Government, for the good of the ſoules ſubject, <hi>was from God;</hi> as how? certainly the other negative part of the contra-diſtinction conſidered, if he ſpeake ſence he muſt meane, by <hi>ordination,</hi> not <hi>permiſſion onely:</hi> but (he ſaies) the <hi>ſinfull meanes by which it,</hi> that is, their actuall poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Power <hi>was accompliſhed, was not from God;</hi> as how? Surely, if he ſpeake reaſon, reaſon will ſay, not by <hi>or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination,</hi> but <hi>permiſſion onely.</hi> As <hi>Jacobs</hi> actual <hi>obtaining</hi> of the bleſsing, was that which God had <hi>ordained;</hi> but his obtaining it by <hi>deceit,</hi> was onely by divine <hi>permiſſion.</hi> And that the Reader may ſee, that when we affirme that the perſon of <hi>Jeroboam</hi> as a Magiſtrate, though not his practiſe as an Uſurper, was from a <hi>divine ordination,</hi> and the power in his hand, though an Uſurper, <hi>the Ordinance of God;</hi> we ſpeake not that which none elſe ever ſpake before; if the judgement of <hi>Paraeus</hi> may be of any mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the point, no man can ſpeake more expreſly; for ſpeaking of Gods rending the Kingdome from <hi>Rebo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoam,</hi> and ſetting up the Kingdome of <hi>Iſrael</hi> in <hi>Jerohoam;</hi> hus he delivers himſelfe, grounding his judgement up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on<note n="*" place="margin">Nec fortuit ò aut hominnm ta tum concilio &amp; pe-fidia, nec deo inſcio aut invito, ſed ita volente &amp; ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance illam <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Regni con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>itu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i onem <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>actam fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſſe, Hiſtoria ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eſta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>1 Reg. 11.31.35,37. 1 Reg. 12.15.24, Parae.</hi> in <hi>Rom. 13. Dub. 3. Ad. 1</hi>
                  </note> the Scripture, <hi>the ſacred Hiſtory doth teſtifie,</hi> 1 Kin. 11.31, 35, 37. 1 <hi>Kin.</hi> 12 15, 14. <hi>The conſtituton of a new Kingdome, came not to paſſe either by accident, or by the councell and treachery of men onely; neither was it without the knowledge, or againſt the will of God, but becauſe hee ordain'd and would have it ſo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Can any thing be ſpoken more plaine from the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:114595:24"/>Text of Scripture, which was alſo urg'd before in the preceding Chapter, to prove, that Government though in the hand of an Uſurper, is the Ordinance of God? and therefore the perſon of the Uſurper, though not his ſinfull entrance by Uſurpation, is by a divine ordination; and ſo a Miniſter of God for our good, which the Exercitator would denye. Tis cleare then and undenyable, that the Exercitator hath laid in a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e principle, as the Corner-ſtone of his whole ſtructure, which being once ſhaken and remov'd, the whole with its whole burthen, like a ruinous building, comes tum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling to the ground. For if (as hath already beene proved) an Uſurper in poſſeſsion be a Magiſtrate, though in reſpect of entrance illegall; and if Government in his hand be (as it hath beene prov'd to be) the Ordinance of God; then it followes beyond contradiction, that the Apoſtle, <hi>Rom</hi> 13. ſpeakes of ſuch incluſively; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſuch in duty muſt be obey'd, and cannot without ſin be reſiſted, which confutes the Exercitators Doctrine, and confirmes the aſſertion of our Author.</p>
               <p>What hath our Antagoniſt to ſay to the Contrary? he would prove that Uſurpers may be reſiſted; and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances moſt abſurdly, in <hi>Chedorlaomer</hi> and his partici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pants, who never were poſſeſt of the Government of <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,</hi> onely made an invaſive War, and tooks ſome Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners; and who ever denyed that an invader or intru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, in that action may be lawfully reſiſted or that to joyn with him in it, were to be equally guilty; but our aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is not againſt reſiding au Uſurper in the Act of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſion, but againſt reſiſting Government in the hand of an intruder, when he is actually poſſeſt of it, and ſo is the onely perſon left us by the providence of God, to be his Miniſter to us for good, in the diſpenſation of that Ordinance, to whom wee may be the cleare and generall Dialect of the Scriptures conclude, that the moſt High, who gives the Kingdome of men to whom be thinkes meet, hath now (to the uttermoſt that were can judge) thought meet to give it.</p>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:114595:25"/>
               <p>His other inſtances are as abſur'd as the former, for they ſpeake onely of a reſiſtance, or rather indeed a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſive War manag'd by publike and ſupreame Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, and thoſe too, all perſons of an <hi>extraordinary</hi> Call, excepting the <hi>Maccabees;</hi> whereas if he would have ſpoken to the purpoſe, he muſt have given an inſtance from Scripture, of ſome private Saint, reſiſting a publike Magiſtrate obtaining, upon pretence, that in his judgement the Title of the Magiſtrate was not good; but that indeed is a taske too hard for the whole Tribe of Exercitators. In the meane time he hath ſufficiently confuted himſelfe in the inſtance concerning <hi>Athaliah,</hi> for ſeeing the Text fares expreſly, <hi>Athaliah</hi> reigned ſix yeares, and all men know there can be no raigning without Subjection, it followes, private perſons muſt be ſubject to Uſurpers in poſſeſsion. Againe, whereas <hi>Jehoiada</hi> and thoſe Rulers over hundreds, ſtirr'd not for <hi>Joaſh</hi> his Right, till the end of ſix yeares; nor then neither, but with ſuch caution as prevented the embroyling of the Common-Wealth, it's cleare that publike perſons and chiefe Magiſtrates, may not remove an Uſurper, in the moſt cleare and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>controverted caſe, with danger and diſturbance to the Common-Wealth. And laſtly, whereas tis ſaid <hi>Athaliah</hi> reigned; tis evident that the Seripture ſpeakes of Uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers in poſſeſsion, as of Magiſtrates, and not private perſons.</p>
               <p>But he urges, <hi>a lawfull calling from the People, is eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentiall to a Magiſtrate.</hi> It is anſwered. Firſt, few King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes in <hi>Europe</hi> have beene ſo begun, or indeed other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe then by conqueſt; and if a conſent of the people come after, what is that but an effect of force? And here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in is briefly, but clearely anſwered, all that hee hath ſaid for the lawfull calling of his Romane Emperours; for what <hi>Tully</hi> (cited by himſelfe) ſaies of one, may with the ſame truth be ſaid concerning all the reſt, <hi>He had</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Attulerat jam liberae civitati, partim meru, partim patien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia, conſuetudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem ſerviendi. <hi>Cicero in M.A Philip. 2. Orar.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>now reduced the Citie</hi> [of Rome] <hi>from a ſtate of libertie, to a cuſtome of ſervitude, partly by feare, and partly by ſuffering.</hi>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:114595:25"/>To which adde that notable teſtimony of <hi>Tacitus,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning <hi>Tiberius</hi> out of his owne mouth. <hi>It is recorded</hi> (ſaies <hi>Tacitus</hi>) <hi>That</hi> Tiberius <hi>as often as he went out of the Senate, was wont to uſe expreſſions aloud in Greeke,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Memorae prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, Tiberum, quoties curia egrederetur, gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis verbis in bunc modum ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qui, ſelitum, OHO MINES AD SERVI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TVIEM PA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RATOS! ſcili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cet etiam illum, qui libertatem publicam nollet, tamprojectae ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vient ium pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entiae taedehat. <hi>Tacit. An. l. 3.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>and to this effect: O men prepared for ſervitude! the trnth is, though him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe were againſt publike Libertie, yet hee loath'd at their baſe patience, in ſubmitting themſelves to ſervitude.</hi> Behold his owne Conſcience condemning him of Vſurpation upon the publike libertie; and yet the Exercitator is not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſham'd to inforce a Title upon him, though therein he op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe himſelfe to the generally received judgement of the moſt approved writers of all ſorts, as were eaſie to ſhew, if time would give leave.</p>
               <p>But Secondly, what if it were granted, that the eſſence of a particular perſons call to the office of Magiſtracy, is ſuch as the Exercitator would have it, yet the eſſence of Magiſtracy it ſelfe, conſiſts not in this call, and may therefore ſubſiſt without it; neither can the diſorder of man, in the manner or circumſtance about the perſon adminiſtring, make the matter or ſubſtance of the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance of God of none effect, no more then the entring into the office of a high Prieſt among the Jewes, by waies corrupt and unwarantable, did null and make void the Office ſelfe, Or to give an inſtance of our owne clear and unqueſtionable; tis well knowne that perſons un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duly choſen Members of Parliament, have properly no Right to fit and Vote in the Houſe; yet their Votes are never the leſſe valid, in any Act of the ſupream Legiſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive power, though afterwards the unduneſſe of the electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on be prov'd, and the perſons diſcharged from further fitting in the Houſe. The like may be ſaid concerning Vſurping Princes of this Nation, whoſe Acts in Law ſtand good at this day, and have a great influence into the preſent Policie among us.</p>
               <p>But here the Exercitator replies, <hi>thereis a miſtake in this argument,</hi> for though thoſe Vſurping Princes <hi>entred by force, or otherwiſe unlawfully; yet they had the concurrent or
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:114595:26"/>ſubſequent conſent of Parliaments.</hi> Was ever man more groſly miſtaken, that would pretend himſelfe an <hi>Ariſtar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chus</hi> over the miſtakes of others? For firſt what power, by his owne grounds hath one that enters by force, or otherwiſe unlawfully, (that is, an Vſurper) to call a Parliament? an Uſurper (if himſelfe ſay true) is no more but a private perſon; and if a private perſon by force, or otherwiſe unlawfully call a Parliament; what is that Parliament but an effect of that force, and unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Act, and therefore it ſelfe unlawfull? for the effect followes the nature of the cauſe. Nay ſecondly, what power (by his owne grounds) hath a Parliament how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever call'd to give away the right from him, hat hath it, to him that hath none? <hi>The people</hi> (or the Exercita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor is miſt ken) <hi>have no power to give their Conſent, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing preing aged to a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s right;</hi> nay their conſent (un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe the Exercitator be fill, in a miſtake) is void and null, and a Parliament (he tells us) hath no power but what the people give them. But thirdly, granting Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments ſo call'd as hath been ſaid, lawfull; and the uſurping Prince <hi>legally inveſted</hi> (as the grand corrector of miſtakes ſpeaks) by thoſe Parliaments, and granting (which is alſo his owne) that the Prince muſt have no hand in conferring any thing to his owne Title, for that were (as he ſaies) a ſelfe-created Titles, when all is paſt, the worſt, is to come for the Exercitater; for from the premiſes, it will inevitably follow. Firſt, that the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preame power is originally properly, and onely in the Houſe of Commons, for they onely are the repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives, and by conſequence the truſtees of the people, and therefore they onely can give a Prince a legall Title; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe (if our Exercitator be not miſtaken in his very foundation) a lawfull calling from the people, is eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall to a Magiſtrate rightly conſtituted. Secondly, it follows clearely, that the ſupreame power is ſo abſolutly in the Houſe of Commons, that they may without wrong take the Kingly authority from him, that had the right
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:114595:26"/>and give both right and it to him that had none. 3ly. It cannot be deny'd, but if they have (as by the premiſes the moſt have) an obſolute power to take the Kingly authority from whom, and give it to whom they thinke meete; they have alſo a power, when they ſhall thinke meete, to reſerve the exerciſe thereof to themſelves; if they ſhall judge it meete for the good of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentees, otherwiſe they ſhould be unfaithfull to their truſt. Laſtly it followes, that the Commons ſit not by ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tue of the Princes call, but their owne right; for an Uſurper (as tis confeſt ſuch were the Princes in queſtion, at the time of the calling) is but a private perſon; and no more (witneſſe our Exercitator) and therefore hath no power to call a Parliament. And now let the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der judge upon the whole, whether ever there were ſuch a <hi>Felo de ſe,</hi> as is this wretched diſcourſe of our Exercita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor: or whether inſtead of correcting one, he hath not ſhew'd himſelfe a thing meerly made up of a heap of miſtakes.</p>
               <p>But to proceed, he tells us page 74 75. That the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of <hi>The lawfulneſſe of obeying</hi> &amp;c. <hi>hath but halfe quoted</hi> Paraeus, <hi>as well as impertinently;</hi> and that, according to Paraeus, <hi>unjuſtly gotten power is not of God, in regard of the perſon, or man owning it, and conſequenly not to be obey'd, by verue of</hi> Rom. 13.</p>
               <p>To doe the Exercitator right,<note place="margin">Nec refert qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus medijs vel artibus <hi>Nimrod Jeroboam</hi> aut alij regra ſibi pa-averint. Nam aliud eſt poteſtas que à deo eſt, aliud acquiſitio &amp; uſus poteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us, que indiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerens, aliàs le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitima, aliàs il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legitina, <hi>Parae.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Rom. 13.</hi>
                  </note> we ſhall take his owne whole quotation of <hi>Paraeus;</hi> and then let the moſt parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Judge, whether he hath not done <hi>Paraeus,</hi> and the Author quoting him; and herein the Reader and him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe worng, in forcing a ſence upon <hi>Paraeus,</hi> ſo much at enmity with his words. Paraeus ſaies, <hi>It matters not by what meanes</hi> Nimrod, Jeroboam, <hi>or others got Kingdoms to themſelves; for the power which is of God is one thing, the getting and uſe of the power is another, which is indifferent, ſometimes lawfull, ſometimes unlawfull.</hi> And againe, <hi>dubijs,</hi> whether both <hi>Paraeus</hi> and the Exercitator himſelf, refers us ſo the fuller explication of this place: <hi>We muſt diſcern betwixt the power which is</hi> EVER <hi>of God, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:114595:27"/>the getting and uſe of the power,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Diſcernendum teſt inter poteſta em que ſemper à Deo eſt, &amp; inter àcquiſitionem &amp; uſurpationem, que quod homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes ſaepe eſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtiſſima, non à Deo, ſed ad ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minem affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus &amp; Statnae Malitia. <hi>Idem. Ibid.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>which as to men is often moſt unjuſt, not of God, but of mens luſts, and Satans malice.</hi> Wherefore to examine the true ſence of the premiſes, and compare them with the Exercitators deduction. <hi>It matters not</hi> (ſaies Paraeus) <hi>by what meanes or craft</hi> Nimrod. Jeroboam <hi>or others:</hi> what others? Our Exercitator ſhall anſwer other <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurper;</hi> for ſuch he hath prov'd <hi>Jeroboam</hi> more then once, beſides, ſuch get Kingdoms to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves by <hi>craft</hi> &amp;c. Again, <hi>It matters not,</hi> ſaies <hi>Paraeus,</hi> in what reſpect matters in not? Reaſon and truth ſhal anſwer in reſpect of their <hi>Authority</hi> to command, and the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects <hi>Duty</hi> to obey. For in the words immediately fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>going; he was proving that <hi>Civil power</hi> is the <hi>Ordinance</hi> of God, and addes, although in the hand of <hi>Nimrod,</hi> or <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roboam,</hi> as he expreſly affirmes, concerning the former <hi>Ad.</hi> 2. <hi>De Nimrodo.</hi> And concerning the latter, as expreſly <hi>Ad</hi> 1 <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 8.4. Laſtly, it matters not, ſaies <hi>Paraeus:</hi> Why matters it not? Why? becauſe the Power howſoever, and by whomſoever got, is EVER of God, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently from him derives its Authority to command; and for him requires our duty to obey, and thus to eye God in our obedience, is to obey according to <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.5. For Conſcience ſake, in the judgement of <hi>Paraeus,</hi> with whom the Annotations of our owne divines concurre. And yet our learned Exercitator ſaies but Sure he ſees not what he ſaies) Paraeus <hi>in your place ſpeakes nothing</hi> pro <hi>or</hi> con <hi>of obedience to <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpers;</hi> when notwithſtanding having travel'd ſome then lines further toward the end of that Paragraph, forgeting that hee had ſaid in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, (ſo treacherous is his memory) that <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raeus</hi> ſpeakes nothing againſt obedience to Vſurpers, he tells us (from the latter quotation, which himſelfe as well as <hi>Paraeus</hi> makes interpretative to ſhe former) he tells us (moſt groſly contradicting himſelf, and the truth) That Paraeus <hi>is againſt obedience to <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpers, by ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of</hi> Rom. 13.<note place="margin">
                     <p>Non quecun<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> per vim vel do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum acquiruntur cum ſint per ſe bona, ceſſant eſſe d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Deo. Diſſere nendum eſt enim interjus dei quod in res bonas nun quam amittis, à quibuscun<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> teneantur: &amp; teneantur; &amp; inter judicia dei puibus bona ſua ſic diſtribuit, ut in eorum acqui ſuione &amp; uſu vitium homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num aliquando concurrere per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittat <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Sic igitur de ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſitione etiam imperiorem &amp; regnorum, quoe Perce, quae Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ci, quae Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni, iujuſtice fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re bellis &amp; op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſionibas ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſiuerunt, eſt judicandum. <hi>Parae.</hi> in <hi>Rom. 13.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </note> Once more and we have done. Paraeus ſaies: <hi>Things that are good in themſelves, ceaſe not to be from
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:114595:27"/>God, bowever gotten by force or fraud. For we muſt diſcerne betwixt the right of God, which he never looſe in good things, by whomſoever, and howſoever poſſeſt: and betwixt the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God, by which he diſtributes his good things ſo, as he ſometimes ſuffers the vitiouſneſſe men to concur in the getting and uſe of them</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Thus thereforo are we to judge of the get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, even of Empiers and Kingdomes, which the</hi> Perſians, <hi>which the</hi> Grecians, <hi>which the</hi> Romans <hi>got, for the most part, by unjust wars and oppreſſions.</hi> And accordingly, <hi>Ad</hi> 2. <hi>De. Nimrodo,</hi> not far before the words cited by the Exercita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor himſelf, Paraeus ſaies, <hi>However Nimrod were an oppreſſor and Tyrant, yet it follows not, that HIS power was not of God:</hi> Yet nor modeſt Exercitator bluſhes not to affirme that Paraeus ſaies, <hi>unjuſtly gotten Power is not of God, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of the perſon, or man owning it.</hi> Could any thing be ſpaken more apparantly, untrue in it ſelf, by one that profeſſes himſelfe ſtudious of truth? more injurious be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond all modeſty, both to <hi>Paraeus,</hi> and the Author quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting him, by an Exercitator pretending to modeſty? yet if he had anſwered without booke againe, it had beene tollerable. But to accuſe his Antagoniſt of a partiall and imperninent quotation; and yet himſelf after a profeſt conſultation with <hi>Paraeus,</hi> to uſe ſuch enforcement, to the cleare letter of the Author, in the faireſt language that can be given it, tis not faire.</p>
               <p>To conclude, tis obſervable here, that whileſt <hi>Paraeus</hi> maintaines the Authority of <hi>Nimrod</hi> and <hi>Jeroboam</hi> to be of God; he neither takes away Uſurpation from them, nor gives them a right Title. And accordingly <hi>Salon,</hi> after he had fully and undeniably prov'd the Duty of obeying the juſt commands of an Uſurper, yet coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels the Uſurper to leave his Vſurpation, and to get the expreſſe conſent of the people. It is not neceſſary there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore (as the Exercitator would infer) that a tacite con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of the people to obey, take away Vſurpation. For the conſent can juſtifie no further then it goes, and it goes no further (in this caſe) then to give Authority
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:114595:28"/>to the Uſurpers juſt commands, for the preſent good of the Common-wealth. And upon this ground, tis that the Law gives Authority to a Lord of M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nnour, though a <hi>Diſſeiſor,</hi> to hold a Court, and the Tenants may ſweare <hi>Fealty</hi> to him, and doe him ſervice, yet nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther juſtifie the Diſſeiſors Tide, nor wrong the Title of the Diſſeiſed.</p>
               <p>There is therefore a <hi>Tacite,</hi> and <hi>Interpretative</hi> conſent of the people (which our Author truly aſſerts, and the Exercitator in vaine denyes) when (as reaſon wills) they conſent that the Power which is peaceably poſſeſt ſhould Governe <hi>pro tempore,</hi> rather then that confution and Warre ſhould deſtroy the Common-Wealth. And ſuch a conſent is ſufficient to conſtitute ſuch a Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate. Wherefore having made good our Aſſertion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſuch Objections in the Exercitation, as are any way materiall; We ſhall profeſſedly omit the reſt. On<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly we cannot but take notice of the wretched folly, and vanitie of his empty challenge Page 75 wherein as he tacitly grants the whole cauſe; ſo he doth it in expreſſe words to any underſtanding Reader. For it obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence be ſubſtantially (as already it hath been) prov'd a Duty; all Circummſtantial Objections vaniſh as a miſt before the Sun.</p>
               <p>And now for a concluſion, (that our Exercitator may end as ill as he began) he goes about to make good the Title of the <hi>Romanes,</hi> to the Kingdome of <hi>Judaea,</hi> even againſt the Title of the Houſe of <hi>David,</hi> and of the great Son of <hi>David;</hi> Chriſt himſelf, who, as Mr. <hi>Perkins</hi> acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges, was right Heire to the Crowne, and Kingdome of the Jewes. And to bring this to paſſe, he leapes over the Beames of Maſſy, and mighty Arguments that lye in his way, and takes up little Motes, and Strawes to binde up this forg'd Title.</p>
               <p>Firſt, He paſſes by the whole Title of the Houſe of <hi>David,</hi> and that great promiſe, <hi>That there ſhould not want a man to ſet on his Throne.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:114595:28"/>
               <p>Secondly, He takes no notice, how the <hi>Maccabees</hi> came by the Kingdome, which was by force and power; when there was another King a Succeſſor of <hi>Alexander,</hi> even of that beaſt in <hi>Daniel,</hi> whoſe Kingdome was devided in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to four parts, yet the Exercitators party condemnes this, if now a Title be thus gotten by Subjects.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, He ſaid nothing of the point, whether the High Prieſt were capable of a Crown, and could bear at once on his head, both a Crown and Mitre; wherein, ſome ſay, he was a patterne of Anti-Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, He obſerves not, that there was a Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of peace and agreement made in the Temple, and bound with Oathes, and confirmed by mutuall em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bracings, betweene <hi>Hircanus</hi> and <hi>Ariſtobulus;</hi> that <hi>Ariſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulus</hi> ſhould command the Kingdome; and this was done in the ſight of all the People.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, He gives no proofe that <hi>Hircanus</hi> having given away the Kingdome before, could give it after to <hi>Pompey;</hi> nor th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t a King at all can give away a Kingdome, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out his Kingdomes conſent. Yea, he cannot prove that he did it: yet this is one of the motes with which h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>inds up <hi>Pompeyes</hi> Title; becauſe <hi>Hircmus,</hi> whoin his opinion, had the better Title (though perchance none at all) untreated him to come to helpe him, and to judge the controverſie betweene him and his Brother: And a ſecond is this, as if <hi>Pompey</hi> had got the good will of the people, to give the Kingdome to him; whereas himſelf ſaith but this, that <hi>Pompey, after he had taken</hi> Jeruſalem, <hi>did rather by good turnes then terrors conciliate the People to himſelfe,</hi> Now this ſpeakes, what <hi>Pompey</hi> did to pleaſe the people, not what the people did to him; much leſſe that they gave up the Kingdome to him, which they would have given to none. For the truth is, <hi>Ioſephus</hi> ſaith; <hi>That all the whole Nation</hi> [marke the words ALL and WHOLE] <hi>were againſt
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:114595:29"/>both</hi> Hircanus <hi>and</hi> Ariſtobulus, <hi>for bringing them under the ſervitude of a Kingdome; For they ſaid, their Cuſtom was to be Governed by Gods High Prieſt.</hi> But I hope <hi>Pompey</hi> was no Prieſt, and therefore they did not chuſe him for their Governour.</p>
               <p>And for the words of <hi>Antipater</hi> concerning <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigonus,</hi> when he craved aſſiſtance from <hi>Caeſar,</hi> they are very untruly alleaged, they being thus in the author: <hi>He,</hi> that is <hi>Antigonus, craved not mainten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance for that he wanted, but that he might raiſe a rebellion among the</hi> Jewes; <hi>and againſt them who ſhould beſtow any thing upon him;</hi> that is againſt <hi>Caeſar,</hi> if he ſhould give him any reliefe. But the Exercitators Latin,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Non propter inopiam deſiderare facultatem ſed ut in eos qui dediſſent Iudaeorum ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditiones accenderet,</hi> is thus conſtrued by him. <hi>He ſought not reliefe of</hi> Caeſar, <hi>becauſe he was poore; but that he might kindle jewiſh ſeditions, againſt theſe had made a dedition of themſelves.</hi> Behold, the foundation of a Kingdome laid upon a falſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of Latin. But is it not a deſperate bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, that this man ſhould take upon him to be a writer, who cannot conſtrue his own Latin; yea that he ſhould put his Latin in the Margent, to ſhame his owne engliſh, eſpecially there being an engliſh Tranſlation, that might have taught him to conſtrue it? But to be ſhort, the ſtory is truly thus, <hi>Hircanus</hi> living quietly after the forementioned Agreement, between him and his Brother, was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually provok't by <hi>Antipater,</hi> (the Father of <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rod</hi>) to ſtirre for the Kingdome; to which at laſt yeilding, and <hi>Pompey</hi> being in thoſe parts, they ſent to <hi>Pompey</hi> concerning their differences, who
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:114595:29"/>gave them audience, and promiſed to came into their Country, to determine their differences, and told them, that in the meane time, they ſhould live in peace.</p>
               <p>But <hi>Ariſtobul us</hi> ſtirring to make himſelf ſtrong, <hi>Pompey</hi> comes up and takes Jeruſalem and Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtobulous alſo, And theu commits the Prieſt-hood to Hireanus, and now ſee the goodly Title of the Romanes in the words of Joſephus, <hi>thus Hireanus and Arriſtrbulous through their diſſentions and evil broyles were the cauſe of that ſervitude and miſery</hi> [not that voluntary ſubjection he ſpeakes of] <hi>that fell upon the Jewes. For we have loſt our liberty and bin ſubdued by the Romanes.</hi> Behold and exellent Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle of the Romanes. Two Brothers being at odds, ſtrive one with another, and deſire Pompety to be an Umpier of their controverſies, therefore the Romanes by this, have a Title to the Crowne of Judaea; or againe, the two Brothers being at odds, Pompey comes in to helpe one againſt the other, and conquers him; who (as the Author ſaies) had the worſe Title. Therefore by beating him, he got a good Title to the Romanes; juſt as if when the Nation deſired helpe of the Scots againſt a Malignant party, the Scots prevaling againſt that party might get a good Title to this whole King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome; or becauſe the Scots deſired the Lievtenant Generall of England, to come for their aſſiſtance into their County againſt the Malignant party there; he might thereupon, or thereby have got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten for the Engliſh a good Title to Scotland. So upon the whole, the Romanes had no other Title but meere Conqueſt; as <hi>Salon,</hi> and many others
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:114595:30"/>do truly affirme, we ſhall now conclude with the reſolution of an holy, impartiall, and reverend Author, and Author of our owne above all excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; as he wrote before theſe times of excepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; hear what he ſaies, concerning the validity of the commands of an uſurped Power and the duty of obeying them.</p>
            </div>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The fault of the worker is when an action of a lawfull calling is done by one that is not called law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, now then when the fault of an action is not in the worke it ſelfe, but in the perſon that worketh is; it is not to be reputed a nullity, neither to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſed as nothing, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>This doctrine is agreed upon by the common conſent of Divines, as alſo by the Lawes, and orders, of Kingdomes, as may appeare plainely in particular.</hi> Auguſtus Caeſar <hi>a Romane Emperour inv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ded the Kingdome of the Jewes, and brought it into a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince: and thus was he made King of the Jewes, not by lawfull meanes, but by intruſion. For all this the Actions done, and the Commandments given by him, were reputed Commandments of a King, not reverſed by any Jew, but obeyed of all. For when he gave Commandment, that all the world; yea the Jewes ſhould he taxed, they yeelded themſelves to this Commandment; yea righteous</hi> Joſeph, <hi>and</hi> Mary <hi>went to their owne Town to be taxed, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>VVhereby it is manifest that if there be no fault in the worke the defective calling of the worker, doth not make a mullity of the Action done. For howſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever the workers ſins, in his unlawfull entrance, and in that regard is not to be approved, yet the Actions in the calling, to which he is en<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>red, are the Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:114595:30"/>of that calling; For though he be called amiſſe, yet he ſtands in the roome of one lawfully called. And we are to make difference betwixt him that is called, though unlawfully, and him that hath no calling at all. For the Actions done without calling, are indeed nul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities, whereas if there be any calling, though entrance <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>dly made, it doth not make the Action void. And whoſoever denieth this ground of truth over-turneth the Regiments of Kingdomes, Churches, States, and ſocieties whatſoever.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
               <bibl>Perkins Treatiſe of callings, Page, 742.</bibl>
            </epigraph>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
